<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great sacrifice of the new law expounded by the figures of the old</title>
            <author>Dymock, James, d. 1718?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 121 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37149</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12574002</idno>
  <idno type="VID">63525</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240969371</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2972</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22878</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12574002</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37149)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 314:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great sacrifice of the new law expounded by the figures of the old</title>
                  <author>Dymock, James, d. 1718?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 202, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to James Dymock. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Pages 53-56 are missing in the filmed copy. Pages 40-65 photographed from Union Theological Seminary Library, New York copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Mass --  Celebration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Lord's Supper --  Catholic Church.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63525:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63525:1"/>
            <p>THE GREAT SACRIFICE OF THE NEW LAW, EXPOUNDED By the Figures OF THE OLD.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Haec munda Oblatio est, quae per varias Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificiorum Naturae &amp; Legis tempore si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudines, figurabatur; velut illorum omnium consummatio &amp; perfectio,</p>
               <bibl>Concil. Trid. Sess. 21. cap. 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>✚</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1676.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Permissu Superiorum.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:63525:2"/>
            <p>Nec pigebit me, sicubi haesito, quaertre; nec pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debit, sicubi erro, discere. Proinde quisquis haec legit, ubi pariter certus est, pergat mecum; ubi pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter haesitat, quaerat mecum; ubi errorem suum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoscit, redeat ad me; ubi meum, revecit me. <bibl>
                  <hi>St. August. lib. 1. de Trin. cap. 2, &amp; 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63525:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS EXCELLENCY DOM FRANCISCO DE MELLO, EMBASSADOR From the most Serene Prince of PORTUGAL To His Majesty of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> and LORD CHAMBERLAIN TO THE QUEEN His Royal Consort, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ESIDES the many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dispensable reasons I have to present this <hi>Exposition of the Mass</hi> to Your EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CELLENCY, the very subject it self seems to oblige me to it. For the <hi>Mass</hi> being an Embassy, as the word <hi>Missa</hi> (from whence it is derived) imports, may be rightly said to claim the Patronage of an Embassador so
<pb facs="tcp:63525:3"/> Illustrious for his piety towards this <hi>August Mystery;</hi> which is indeed a Sacred Embassy from the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> to God the Father by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery of her Priests, who in the name of all Mankind negociat affairs of highest importance, as are the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of subjection and vassalage of the Creature to his Creatour, and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord. His grateful thanks for the dayly and reiterated benefits he receives from his divine hands. His submissive supplications of pardon for offences committed against his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majesty: And finally his humble petitions for new favours, and Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings from his bounteous liberality.</p>
            <p>Hence appears the great Office of the <hi>Priest</hi> at the Altar, being there in quality of an Embassador and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitour general of all Mankind: <hi>Pro Christo legatione fungimur,</hi> said S. <hi>Paul</hi> for himself, and for all Priests.</p>
            <p>These and the like considerations, have induced Your EXCELLENCY
<pb facs="tcp:63525:3"/> to adorn with so much care and cost, that Sacred place where this Divine Mystery is dayly Celebrated: For which reason I wish that this <hi>Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> may fly like the Prophet <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias</hi> wing'd Rowl, <hi>Video volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men volans,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Cap. 5. 2.</note> to publish to the World Your transcendent zeal, and how much You delight like <hi>David,</hi> to deck up the House of God, with Your own hands.</p>
            <p>But here Your EXCELLENCIES known aversion from hearing what may savour of Your own praise, checks the forwardness of my pen, not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving me leave in speaking of Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to reveal those of Your solid and discret Piety; but, forcing me to an unwilling silence, permits me only to subscribe my self</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>YOUR EXCELLENCIES Most humble and devoted Servant J. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:63525:4"/>
            <head>✚ ✚ ✚</head>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE Illustrious Saint of this last age Bishop <hi>Sales,</hi> had good reason to call the Holy Sacrifice of the <hi>Mass,</hi> The Center of Christian Religion, the heart of Devotion, and the Soul of Piety; <hi>Introd. lib. 2. cap.</hi> 14. since that at <hi>Mass,</hi> it is not the <hi>Church</hi> alone that adores God, as she doth in her other Offices; but it is <hi>Christ</hi> himself (who being God) offers to his Father, the most perfect homage that can be pay'd him.</p>
            <p>The concern of Christianity in this Great Mystery, hath stirr'd up diverse Persons of Learning, and Piety to illustrate it with their writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. The Learned have much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to inform the Curious, touching the Antiquity and variety
<pb facs="tcp:63525:4"/> of each part of the <hi>Mass.</hi> But these discourses, though learnedly instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, seem not directly to aim at the improving of our Piety at this Great Sacrifice. Others have grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd the People with several Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods for hearing <hi>Mass:</hi> But as I humbly conceive, they are ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed rather upon Mystical Exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions relating to the Life and Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of <hi>Christ,</hi> than upon the literal grounds of a true and perfect Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which the <hi>Mass</hi> essentially is.</p>
            <p>Those I have seen, seem rather to explain the accidental Ceremonies, than the Sacrifice it self. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, they are very exact to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us, when, and who ordained Water to be mingled with Wine? what is signify'd by this Water? why the Priest blesses the Water, and not the Wine? and why he doth not bless it at <hi>Masses</hi> for the Dead? Finally, why he puts so little Water into it? But seldom or never
<pb facs="tcp:63525:5"/> throughly inform us of the main de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign intended herein by the <hi>Church,</hi> who notwithstanding terms it a Great Mystery; <hi>Per hujus aquae &amp; vini mysterium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Supposing then <hi>Transubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> as an Article of our Faith, which any may see satisfactorily prov'd in our ancient and modern Authors, I here endeavour to expound the most essential parts of the <hi>Mass,</hi> by proofs deduced chiefly out of the Sacred Books of <hi>Exodus,</hi> and <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus;</hi> making use of the Figures and Sacrifices of the Old Law, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain and prove the Sacrifice of the New; they evidencing the <hi>Mass</hi> to be a compleat and perfect Sacrifice, without tedious controversy, or sharp contest. So did <hi>Christ</hi> himself expound to <hi>Nicodemus</hi> the Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross,</hi> by the figure of the <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> long before erected in the Desert, <hi>John</hi> 3. 14.</p>
            <p>I hope no <hi>Catholick</hi> will take ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions,
<pb facs="tcp:63525:5"/> if after four <hi>English</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slations of the <hi>Mass</hi> by <hi>Catholicks,</hi> I set forth a fifth, of one entire <hi>Mass,</hi> for a greater light to this annexed Exposition, which would be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably disadvantaged by the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of the Text it self. And so many previous examples, will, I am confident, with the Prudent, prove a sufficient Apology. <hi>Idolatry</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed had good cause to keep its <hi>Arcana,</hi> unknown to the People, as an artifice to cover its shame from derision. But Religion, in due cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances, justly glories in publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Mysteries, when a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Translation unveils them with splendour.</p>
            <p>'Tis true the <hi>Church</hi> for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving uniformity, hath retained in her publick Liturgies the <hi>Latine</hi> Tongue, as the most universally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood by all Nations. But since the same Church hath strickly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged all Pastors to expound to
<pb facs="tcp:63525:6"/> the People the Mysteries of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Sacrifice: <hi>Ne oves Christi pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reant.... mandat sancta Synodus... ut frequenter sanctissimi hujus Sacrificii mysterium aliquod declarent, diebus praesertim Dominicis; Concil. Trid. Sess. 22. cap.</hi> 8. And that she recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends this afresh, in her admirable Catechism: <hi>Hoc igitur Mysterium Parochi diligenter exponant, ut cum fideles ad rem divinam convenerint, attente, &amp; religiose sacra in quibus interfunt, meditari discant; Catech. Trid. p. 2. de Euch. n.</hi> 69. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, since the calamity of times hinder generally with us, a publick and Pastoral Exposition, I presume those that want it, will accept (with the same charity as it is offer'd) this little Book, which will prove easy to the meanest capacity, if their neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity can so far prevail with their spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Directours, as sometimes to exemplify upon a table, the Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotal Actions which correspond to
<pb facs="tcp:63525:6"/> the respective Parts of this Exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Mass.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, it may prove useful in several respects, not only to Lay-Catholicks, and in some sort to Priests; but even to <hi>Protestants.</hi> First, advantaging Laye-Catholicks, who have not the knowledge of the <hi>Latine</hi> Tongue, in the best way of hearing <hi>Mass,</hi> by accompanying the Priest all along; instead of say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>Beads</hi> or other Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: For though these are excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in their kind, yet are they not very seasonable during the Sacrifice of the <hi>Mass.</hi> Next to teach them to serve at <hi>Mass,</hi> the Answers of the <hi>Clerk</hi> being pointed out to them by the letter <hi>R,</hi> or <hi>Resp.</hi> As for Priests, it is portable in the pocket; and for want of a better, may be made use of, it containing entirely <hi>The Votive Mass of the Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Trinity,</hi> purposely chosen, as the fittest to be said upon several occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions.
<pb facs="tcp:63525:7"/> Lastly, to undeceive sincere and misinformed <hi>Protestants,</hi> who represent to themselves this <hi>Mystery of Holiness,</hi> as a Mystery of abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; or at the best, but as a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in <hi>Latine,</hi> and consequently insignificant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Introit, Collect, Epistle, Gradual, Offertory, &amp;c.</hi> are here purposely printed in an Old <hi>English</hi> Letter, to si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnify that they varie almost every day throughout the whole Year; and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently are here brought in, for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample only.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:63525:7"/>
            <p>ORDO MISSAE.</p>
            <p>THE HOLY MASS.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:63525:8"/>
            <head>ORDO MISSAE.</head>
            <sp>
               <stage>Sacerdos ad gradum Altaris, dicit:</stage>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Nomine Patris, &amp; Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii, &amp; Spiritus Sancti, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>Introibo ad Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare Dei.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>Populus respondet.</stage>
               <p>Ad Deum qui laetificat juventutem meam.</p>
            </sp>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="Psalm">
                        <head>Psalmus 42.</head>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>S.</speaker>
                           <p>JUdica me Deus &amp; discerne causam meam de gente non sancta: ab homine iniquo &amp; doloso erue me.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
                           <p>Quia tu es Deus fortitudo mea, quare me repulisti? &amp; quare tristis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedo dum affligit me inimicus?</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>S.</speaker>
                           <p>Emitte lucem tuam &amp; veritatem tuam: ipsa me deduxerunt &amp; adduxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt in Montem Sanctum Tuum &amp; in Tabernacula Tua.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63525:9"/>
                           <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
                           <p>Et introibo ad Altare Dei: ad Deum qui laetificat juventutem meam.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>P.</speaker>
                           <p>Confitebor tibi in cythara, Deus, Deus meus: quare tristis es anima mea, &amp; quare conturbas me?</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
                           <p>Spera in Deo, quoniam adhuc Confitebor illi: Salutare vultus mei, &amp; Deus meus.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>P.</speaker>
                           <p>Gloria Patri, &amp; Filio, &amp; Spiritu Sancto.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
                           <p>Sicut erat in principio, &amp; nunc, &amp; semper, &amp; in saecula saeculorum. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <stage>In Missis pro Defunctis, &amp; a Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica Passionis, usque ad Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam Resurrectionis, dicto, <hi>In no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Patris,</hi> Sacerdos hic inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit:</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>INtroibo ad Altare Dei.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>Ad Deum qui laetificat juventutem meam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Adjutorium nostrum in nomine Domine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>Qui fecit Coelum &amp; Terram.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Sacerdos dicit:</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Confiteor Deo omnipotenti, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
               <p>Misereatur vestri omnipotens
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63525:10"/> Deus, &amp; dimissis peccatis tuis, perdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat te ad vitam aeternam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
               <p>Confiteor Deo omnipotenti, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atae <hi>Mariae</hi> semper Virgini, beato <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeli</hi> Archangelo, beato <hi>Joanni Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stae,</hi> Sanctis Apostolis <hi>Petro</hi> &amp; <hi>Paulo,</hi> om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Sanctis, &amp; tibi Pater: quia pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavi nimis cogitatione, verbo &amp; opere: Mea culpa, mea culpa, mea maxima culpa. Ideo precor beatam <hi>Mariam</hi> sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Virginem, beatum <hi>Michaelem</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angelum, beatum <hi>Joannem Baptistam,</hi> Sanctos Apostolos <hi>Petrum</hi> &amp; <hi>Paulum,</hi> omnes Sanctos, &amp; te Pater, orare pro me ad Dominum Deum nostrum.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Misereatur vestri omnipotens Deus, &amp; dimissis peccatis vestris, perducat vos ad vitam aeternam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
               <p>Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Indulgentiam, absolutionem, &amp; remissionem peccatorum vestrorum, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buat vobis omnipotens &amp; misericors Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
               <p>Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Deus tu conversus vivificabis nos.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
               <p>Et Plebs tua laetabitur in te.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Ostende nobis Domine, misericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam tuam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
               <p>Et salutare tuum da nobis:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:63525:11"/>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Domine exaudi orationem meam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
               <p>Et clamor meus ad te veniat.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Dominus vobiscum.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
               <p>Et cum Spiritu tuo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>Sacerdos ascendens ad Altare, dicit:</stage>
               <p>Aufer à nobis quaesumus, Domine, iniquitates nostras: ut ad Sancta San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum, puris mereamur mentibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troire, per Christum Dominum nostrum. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>Quum Sacerdos ad Altare ascende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, inclinatus dicit.</stage>
               <p>Oramus te Domine, per merita San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum tuorum quorum Reliquiae hic sunt, &amp; omnium Sanctorum, ut indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere digneris omnia peccata mea. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:63525:12"/>
               <head>MISSA DE S. S. TRINITATE.</head>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="introit">
                           <head>Introitus.</head>
                           <p>BEnedicta sit Sancta Trinitas, atque indivisa unitas: confitebimur ei quia fecit nobiscum misericordiam suam. <hi>Psal.</hi> 8. Domine Dominus noster, quam admirabile est nomen tuum in universa Terra. <hi>V.</hi> Gloria Patri, &amp; Filio, &amp; Spiritui Sancto. Sicut erat in princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio, &amp; nunc, &amp; semper, &amp; in saecula saecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Kyrie eleyson.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Kyrie eleyson.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Kyrie eleyson.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Christe eleyson.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Christe eleyson.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Christe eleyson.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Kyrie eleyson.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Kyrie eleyson.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Kyrie eleyson.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Sequitur <hi>Gloria in Excelsis,</hi> quod non dicitur in Missis Defunctorum, nec in Quodragesima, nec in Festis, nec
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63525:13"/> in Votivis, nec Vigiliis, nisi sit Angelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,, &amp; B. <hi>Mariae</hi> in Sabatho.</stage>
                  <p>GLoria in excelsis Deo, &amp; in Terra pax hominibus bonae voluntatis, lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus te, benedicimus te, adoramus te, glorisicamus te, gratias agimus tibi pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter magnam Gloriam tuam; Domine Deus Rex Coelestis. Deus Pater omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potens. Domine Fili Unigenite <hi>Jesu Christe.</hi> Domine Deus Agnus Dei, Fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Patris, qui tollis peccata Mundi, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serere nobis: qui tollis peccata Mundi, suscipe deprecationem nostram: qui se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ad Dextram Patris miserere nobis, quoniam tu solus Sanctus, tu solus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus, tu solus Altissimus <hi>Jesu Christe,</hi> cum Sancto Spiritu, In Gloria Dei Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Sacerdos vertens se ad Populum, dicit:</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Dominus vobiscum,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Et cum Spiritu tuo.</p>
               </sp>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>Oratio seu Collecta.</head>
                           <p>OMnipotens sempiterne Deus, qui dedisti famulis tuis in confessione verae Fidei, aeternae Trinitatis gloriam agnoscere, &amp; in potentia Majestatis ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare unitatem: quaesumus ut ejusdem
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63525:14"/> fidei firmitate, ab omnibus semper mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niamur adversis. Per Dominum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum Iesum Christum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="lesson">
                           <head>Lectio Epistolae beati <hi>Pauli</hi> Apostoli, ad Corinthios, <hi>Cap.</hi> 13.</head>
                           <p>FRatres. Gaudete, perfecti estote, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortamini, idem sapite, pacem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bete: &amp; Deus pacis &amp; dilectionis erit vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biscum. Gratia Domini nostri <hi>Jesu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti,</hi> &amp; charitas Dei, &amp; communicatio San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti Spiritus sit cum omnibus vobis <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Graduale.</hi> Benedictus es Domine, qui intueris abyssos, &amp; sedes super Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubim.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>V.</hi> Benedictus es Domine in Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mamento Coeli, &amp; laudabilis in saecula. <hi>Alleluja, Alleluja.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>V.</hi> Benedictus es Domine Deus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum nostrorum, &amp; laudabilis in saecula. <hi>Alleluja.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>Oratio ante Evangelium.</head>
                           <p>MUnda cor meum &amp; labia mea, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotens Deus, qui labia <hi>Isaiae</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetae calculo mundasti ignito: Ita me tua grata miseratione dignare mundare, ut Sanctum Evangelium tuum digne va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leam
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63525:15"/> nuntiare, per Christum Dominum nostrum. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Jube Domine benedicere.</p>
               <p>Dominus sit in Corde meo &amp; in labiis meis, ut digne &amp; competenter annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiem Evangelium suum. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Dominus vobiscum.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Et cum Spiritu tuo.</p>
               </sp>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="reading">
                           <head>Sequentia Sancti Evangelii, secundum <hi>Joannem,</hi> Cap. 15.</head>
                           <p>IN illo tempore, dixit <hi>Jesus</hi> Discipulis suis, Cum venerit Paralitus quem ego mittam vobis a Patre Spiritum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis, qui a Patre procedit: ille testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium perhibebit de me. Et vos testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium perhibebitis; quia ab initio mecum estis. Haec locutus sum vobis, ut non scandalizemini. Absque Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogis facient vos: Sed venit hora, ut omnis qui interficit vos, arbitretur ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequium se praestare Deo. Et haec fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vobis, quia non noverunt Patrem, neque me. Sed haec locutus sum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis: ut cum venerit hora, eorum remi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niscamini, quia ego dixi vobis.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Laus tibi <hi>Christe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:63525:16"/>
                  <stage>Tunc Sacerdos submissa voce, dicit:</stage>
                  <p>Per Evangelica dicta deleantur no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra delicta. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Tunc dicitur <hi>Credo,</hi> quando dicendum est:</stage>
                  <p>CRedo in unum Deum Patrem omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentem, Factorem Coeli &amp; Terrae, visibilium omnium &amp; invisibilium Et in unum Dominum <hi>Jesum Christum</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Dei unigenitum. Et ex Patre na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ante omnia saecula. Deum de Deo, Lumen de Lumine, Deum verum de Deo vero. Genitum non factum: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantialem Patri, per quem omnia fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta sunt. Qui propter nos homines, &amp; propter nostram salutem descendit de Coelis. Et incarnatus est de Spiritu San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto, ex Maria Virgine. ET HOMO FACTUS EST: Crucifixus etiam pro nobis, sub <hi>Pontio Pilato</hi> passus &amp; sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus est, &amp; resurrexit tertia die secundum Scripturas, &amp; ascendit in Coelum, sedet ad dexteram Patris. Et iterum venturus est cum gloria Judicare vivos &amp; mortuos: cujus Regni non erit finis. Et in Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Sanctum, Dominum &amp; vivifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63525:17"/> qui ex Patre Filioque procedit. Qui cum Patre &amp; Filio simul adoratur, &amp; conglorificatur, qui loquutus est per Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetas; Et unam Sanctam Catholicam &amp; Apostolicam Ecclesiam: Confiteor u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Baptisma in remissionem peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Et expecto resurrectionem mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuorum, &amp; vitam venturi saeculi. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Dominus vobiscum.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Et cum Spiritu tuo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Oremus.</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Offertorium.</hi> Benedictns sit Deus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, unigenitusque Dei Filius, Sanctus quoque Spiritus: quia fecit nobiscum misericordiam suam.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Hostiam offerens, dicit:</stage>
                  <p>SUscipe Sancte Pater, omnipotens ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne Deus, hanc immaculatam Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiam, quam ego indignus famulus tuus offero tibi Deo meo vivo &amp; vero, pro in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerabilibus peccatis, &amp; offensionibus &amp; negligentiis meis, &amp; pro omnibus cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstantibus, sed &amp; pro omnibus fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Christianis vivis atque defunctis: ut mihi &amp; illis proficiat ad Salutem in vitam aeternam. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:63525:18"/>
                  <stage>Aquam miscendam in Calice benedicit, dicens:</stage>
                  <p>DEus qui Humanae substantiae dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem mirabiliter condidisti, &amp; mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilius reformasti: Da nobis per hujus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae, &amp; Vini Mysterium, ejus Divinitatis esse Consortes, qui Humanitatis nostrae fieri dignatus est particeps, <hi>Jesus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus</hi> Filius tuus Dominus noster: qui te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum vivit &amp; regnat in unitate Spiritus Sancti Deus, per omnia saecula saeculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Calicem offert dicens:</stage>
                  <p>OFferimus tibi Domine Calicem salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taris, tuam deprecantes clementiam: ut in conspectu Divinae Majestatis tuae, pro nostra &amp; totius Mundi salute cum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore suavitatis ascendat. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Inclinatus, dicit:</stage>
                  <p>INspiritu humilitatis, &amp; in animo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trito suscipiamur à te Domine, &amp; sic fiat Sacrificium nostrum in conspectu tuo hodie, ut placeat tibi Domine Deus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Benedicens Panem &amp; Vinum, dicit:</stage>
                  <p>VEni Sanctificator, omnipotens aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Deus, &amp; benedic hoc Sacrificium tuo sancto nomini praeparatum.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63525:19"/> Lavat manus, dicens:</stage>
                  <p>LAvabo inter innocentes manus meas, &amp; circumdabo Altare tuum Domine.</p>
                  <p>Ut audiam vocem Laudis; &amp; enar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem universa mirabilia tua.</p>
                  <p>Domine dilexi decorem dornus tuae, &amp; Locum habitationis Gloriae tuae.</p>
                  <p>Ne perdas cum impiis, Deus, animam meam, &amp; cum viris Sanguinum vitam meam.</p>
                  <p>In quorum manibus iniquitates sunt, dextera eorum repleta est muneribus.</p>
                  <p>Ego autem in innocentia mea ingres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus sum: redime me &amp; miserere mei.</p>
                  <p>Pes meus stetit in directo: in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siis benedicam te Domine.</p>
                  <p>Gloria Patri, &amp; Filio, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>In Missis pro Defunctis, &amp; tempore Passionis in Missis de tempore, omittitur <hi>Gloria Patri.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Inclinatus in medio Altaris dicit:</stage>
                  <p>SUscipe Sancta Trinitas, hanc oblatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, quam tibi offerimus ob memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam Passionis, Resurrectionis, &amp; Ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionis <hi>Jesu Christi</hi> Domini nostri: &amp; in honore beatae <hi>Mariae</hi> semper Virginis, &amp; beati <hi>Joannis Baptistae,</hi> &amp; Sanctorum A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolorum <hi>Petri</hi> &amp; <hi>Pauli:</hi> &amp; istorum, &amp;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63525:20"/> omnium Sanctorum; ut illis proficiat ad honorem, nobis autem ad salutem: &amp; illi pro nobis intercedere dignentur in Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, quorum memoriam agimus in terris. Per Dominum nostrum. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Versus ad Populum, dicit;</stage>
                  <p>ORate, fratres, ut meum ac vestrum Sacrificium acceptabile fiat apud Deum Patrem omnipotentem.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Cui Populus respondet;</stage>
                  <p>SUscipiat Dominus hoc Sacrificium de manibus tuis, ad laudem &amp; gloriam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis sui, ad utilitatem quoque nostram, totiusque Ecclesiae suae sanctae.</p>
               </sp>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>Secreta.</head>
                           <p>SAnctifica, quaesumus Domine Deus noster, per tui sancti nominis invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationem, hujus oblatiouis Hostiam, &amp; per eam nosmetipsos tibi perfice munus aeternum. Per Dominum nostrum Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum Christum Filium tuum, qui tecum vivit &amp; reguat in unitate Spiritus san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti <hi>Deus.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <stage>Secreta Oratione finita, clara voce dicit, Sequentia <hi>Per omnia,</hi> &amp;c.</stage>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:63525:21"/>
               <head>PRAEFATIO COMMƲNIS.</head>
               <p>PEr omnia saecula saeculorum.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Dominus vobiscum.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Et cum Spiritu tuo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Sursum corda.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Habemus ad Dominum.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Gratias agamus Domino Deo nostro.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Dignum &amp; justum est.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>VEre dignum &amp; justum est, aequum &amp; salutare; nos tibi semper &amp; ubique gratias agere: Domine Sancte, Pater om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotens aeterne Deus: Per Christum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum nostrum. Per quem Majestatem tuam laudant Angeli, adorant Domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, tremunt Potestates; Coeli coelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque Virtutes, ac beata Seraphim, so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia exultatione concelebrant. Cum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; nostras voces, ut admitti jubeas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precamur, supplici confessione dicentes.</p>
               <p>Sanctus, Sanctus, Sanctus, Dominus Deus Sabbaoth. Pleni sunt Coeli &amp; Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra gloria tua. Hosanna in excelsis. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictus
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63525:22"/> qui venit in nomine Domini. Hosanna in excelsis.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="preface">
                           <head>Praefatio de B. Trinitate.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>VEre dignum &amp; justum est, aequum, &amp; salutare nos tibi semper &amp; ubique gratias agere: Domine, sancte Pater Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotens aeterne Deus. Qui cum Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genito Filio tuo, &amp; Spiritu sancto, unus es Deus unus es Dominus: non in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us singularitate personae, sed in unius Trinitate substantiae. Quod enim de tua gloria, revelante te credimus, hoc de Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio tuo, hoc de Spiritu sancto, sine diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia discretionis sentimus. Vt in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessione verae sempiternaeque Deitatis, &amp; in personis proprieras, &amp; in essentia uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, &amp; in Majestate adoretur aequalitas. Quam laudant Angeli, atque Archange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, Checubim quoque ac Seraphim: qui non cessant clamare quotidie, una voce dicentes, Sanctus, Sanctus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:63525:23"/>
               <head>CANON MISSAE.</head>
               <p>TE igitur, clementissime Pater, per Jesum Christum filium tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Dominum nostrum suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces rogamus, ac petimus, uti accepta ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas, &amp; benedicas, haec ✚ dona, haec ✚ munera, haec ✚ sancta Sacrificia illibata, in primis, quae tibi offerimus pro Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia tua sancta Catholica, quam paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficare, custodire, adunare, &amp; regere dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris toto orbe terrarum, una cum Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulo tuo Papa nostro <hi>N.</hi> &amp; Antistite no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stro <hi>N.</hi> necnon &amp; Rege nostro <hi>N.</hi> &amp; omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus orthodoxis atque Catholicae &amp; Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicae fidei cultoribus.</p>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Commemoratio pro Vivis.</stage>
                  <p>Memento, Domine, famulorum famu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larumque tuarum <hi>N.</hi> et <hi>N.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Orat aliquantulum pro quibus orare intendit.</stage>
                  <p>Et omnium circumstantium quorum
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63525:24"/> tibi fides cognita est &amp; nota devotio, pro quibus tibi offerimus, vel qui tibi offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt hoc Sacrificium laudis pro se, suis{que} omnibus, pro redemptione animarum suarum, pro spe salutis, &amp; incolumitatis suae, tibique reddunt vota sua aeterno Deo, vivo et vero.</p>
                  <p>Communicantes, et memoriam vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes, in primis gloriosae semper Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Mariae Genitricis Dei, &amp; Domini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stri Jesu Christi, sed &amp; beatorum Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum &amp; Martyrum tuorum, Petri &amp; Pauli, Andreae, Jacobi, Joannis, Thomae, Jacobi, Philippi, Bartholomaei, Matthaei, Simonis &amp; Thadaei, Lini, Cleti, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis, Xisti, Cornelii, Cypriani, Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentii, Chrysogoni, Joannis &amp; Pauli, Cosmae &amp; Damiani, &amp; omnium Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tuorum, quorum meritis precibus{que} concedas, ut in omnibus protectionis tuae muniamur auxilio. Per eundem Christum Dominum nostrum. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Tenens manus expansas super Oblata, dicit:</stage>
                  <p>HAnc igitur Oblationem servitutis nostrae, sed &amp; cunctae familiae tuae, quaesumus Domine, ut placatus accipias:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63525:25"/> diesque nostros in tua pace disponas, at que ab aeterna damnatione nos eripi, &amp; in Electorum tuorum jubeas grege nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merari. Per Christum Dominum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum. Amen.</p>
                  <p>Quam Oblationem tu Deus in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quaesumus, benedictam, adscriptam, ratam, rationabilem, acceptabilemque sacere digneris, ut nobis Corpus, &amp; San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis fiat dilectissimi Filli tui Domini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stri Jesu Christi.</p>
                  <p>Qui pridie quam pateretur, accepit pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem in sanctas ac venerabiles manus suas, &amp; elevatis oculis in coelum, ad te Deum Patrem suum Omnipotentem, tibi gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias agens, benedixit, fregit, dedit{que} Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipulis suis, dicens: Accipite &amp; mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ex hoc omnes, HOC EST ENIM CORPUS MEUM.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Genuflexus adorat, surgit, ostendit Populo.</stage>
                  <p>Simili modo postquam coenatum est, accipiens &amp; hunc praeclarum Calicem in sanctas ac venerabiles manus suas, item tibi gratias agens, benedixit, deditque Discipulis suis, dicens: Accipite &amp; bibite ex eo omnes, HIC EST ENIM CALIX SANGUINIS MEI, Novi &amp; Eterni Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stamenti,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63525:26"/>
[Mysterium Fidei] qui pro vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis &amp; pro multis effundetur in remissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem peccatorum.</p>
                  <p>Haec quotiescumque fecerits, in mei memoriam facietis.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Genuflexus adorat, surgit, ostendit Populo.</stage>
                  <p>UNde &amp; memores, Domine, nos servi tui, sed &amp; plebs tua Sancta, ejus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Christi Filii tui Domini nostri tam beatae Passionis, necnon ab inferis Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectionis, sed &amp; in Coelos gloriosae As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censionis; offerimus praeclarae Majesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti tuae de tuis donis ac datis, Hostiam puram, Hostiam sanctam, Hostiam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculatam, Panem sanctum vitae aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, &amp; Calicem salutis perpetuae.</p>
                  <p>Supra quae propitio ac sereno vultu re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicere digneris, &amp; accepta habere sicuti accepta habere dignatus es munera pueri tui justi Abel, &amp; Sacrificium Patriarchae nostri Abrahamae; &amp; quod tibi obtulit Summus Sacerdos tuus Melchisedec, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum Sacrificium, Immaculatam Hostiam.</p>
                  <p>Supplices te rogamus, Omnipotens Deus; jube haec praeferri per manns san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti Angeli tui in sublime Altare tuum, in conspectu divinae Majestatis tuae, ut
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63525:27"/> quotquot ex hac Altaris participatione, Sacrosanctum Filii tui Corpus &amp; Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem sumpserimus, omni benedictione coelesti, &amp; gratia repleamur. Per eundem Christum Dominum nostrum. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Commemoratio pro Defunctis.</stage>
                  <p>MEmento etiam, Domine, famulorum famularumque tuarum <hi>N.</hi> &amp; <hi>N.</hi> qui nos praecesserunt cum signo Fidei, &amp; dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miunt in somno pacis.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Orat aliquantulum pro iis Defunctis, pro quibus orare intendit.</stage>
                  <p>Ipsis Domine, &amp; omnibus in Christo quiescentibus, locum refrigerii, Lucis &amp; Pacis, ut indulgeas deprecamur. Per eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Christum Dominum nostrum. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Manu percut it sibi pectus.</stage>
                  <p>NObis quoque peccatoribus famulis tuis, de multitudine miserationum tuarumsperantibus, partem aliquam &amp; so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietatem donare digneris, cum tuis sanctis Apostolis &amp; Martyribus, cum Joanne, Stephano, Matthia, Barnaba, Ignatio,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63525:28"/> Alexandro, Marcellino, Petro, Felicitate, Perpetua, Agatha, Lucia, Agnete, Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia, Anastasia, &amp; omnibus Sanctis tuis: intra quorum nos consortium non aesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mator meriti, sed veniae, quaesumus largi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor admitte. Per Christum Dominum nostrum.</p>
                  <p>Per quem haec omnia, Domine, semper bona creas, sanctificas, vivificas, benedicis, &amp; praestas nobis. Per ipsum, &amp; in ipso, &amp; cum ipso, est tibi Deo Patri Omnipotenti in unitate Spiritus Sancti, omnis honor &amp; gloria. Per omnia saecula saeculorum.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Oremus.</stage>
                  <p>PRaeceptis salutaribus moniti, &amp; divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na institutione formati, audemus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere:</p>
                  <p>Pater noster, qui es in coelis, san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctificetur nomen tuum: adveniat regnum tuum, fiat voluntas tua, sicut in coelo, &amp; in terra: Panem nostrum quotidianum da nobis hodie; &amp; dimitte nobis debita no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra, sicut &amp; nos dimittimus debitoribus nostris. Et ne nos inducas in tentatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
                  <p>Sed libera nos à malo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:63525:29"/>
                  <p>Libera nos, quaesumus Domine, ab om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus malis, praeteritis, praesentibus &amp; fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis: &amp; intercedente beata &amp; gloriofa semper Virgine Dei Genitrice Maria, cum beatis Apostolis tuis Petro &amp; Paulo, atque Andraea, &amp; omnibus Sanctis, da propitius pacem in diebus nostris: ut ope misericordiae tuae adjuti, &amp; à peccato si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus semper liberi, &amp; ab omni perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione securi. Per eundem Dominum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum Jesum Christum Filium tuum, qui tecum vivit &amp; regnat in unitate Spiritus Sancti Deus: Per omnia saecula saeculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Pax Domini sit semper vobiscum.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
                  <p>Et cum Spiritu tuo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Particulam Hostiae immittit in Calicem, dicens secreto:</stage>
                  <p>Haec commixtio &amp; consecratio Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris &amp; Sanguinis Domini nostri Jesu Christi, fiat accipientibus nobis in vitam aeternam. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Inclinatus Sacramento, &amp; ter-pectus percu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiens, dicit:</stage>
                  <p>AGnus Dei, qui tollis peccata mundi, miserere nobis.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:63525:30"/>
                  <p>Agnus Dei, qui tollis peccata mundi, miserere nobis.</p>
                  <p>Agnus Dei, qui tollis peccata mundi, dona nobis pacem.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>In Missis pro Defunctis non dicitur, <hi>Mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere nobis,</hi> sed ejus loco, <hi>Dona eis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiem;</hi> &amp; in tertio additur, <hi>sempiter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>DOmine Jesu Christe, qui dixisti Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolis tuis, Pacem relinquo vobis, pacem meam do vobis; ne respicias pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata mea, sed fidem Ecclesiae tuae: eam{que} secundum voluntatem tuam pacificare &amp; coadunare digneris: Qui vivis &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnas Deus. Per omnia saecula saeculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>In Missis Defunctorum non dicitur prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedens Oratio.</stage>
                  <p>DOmine Jesu Christe, Fili Dei vivi, qui ex voluntate Patris, cooperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Spiritu Sancto, per mortem tuam Mundum vivificasti: libera me per hoc Sacro-sanctum Corpus &amp; Sanguinem tuum, ab omuibus iniquitatibus meis, &amp; universis malis; &amp; fac me tuis semper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerere mandatis, &amp; à te nunquam separari
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63525:31"/> permittas: qui cum eodem Deo Patre &amp; Spiritu Sancto vivis &amp; regnas Deus in saecula saeculorum, Amen.</p>
                  <p>PErceptio Corporis tui, Domine Jesu Christe, quod ego indignus sumere praesumo, non mihi proveniat in judicium &amp; condemnationem; sed pro tua pietate prosit tui ad tutamentum mentis &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris, &amp; ad medelam percipiendam: qui vivis &amp; regnas cum Deo Patre, in unitate Spiritus sancti Deus, per omnia saecula saeculorum. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Genuflectit, surgit, &amp; Hostiam accipiens, dicit:</stage>
                  <p>PAnem Coelestem accipiam, &amp; nomen Domini invocabo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Percutiens pectus, dicit ter devote &amp; humiliter.</stage>
                  <p>DOmine, non sum dignus; ut intres sub tectum meum, sed tantum dic verbo, &amp; sanabitur anima mea.</p>
                  <p>Domine, non sum dignus; ut intres sub tectum meum, sed tantum dic verbo, &amp; sanabitur anima mea.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:63525:32"/>
                  <p>Domine, non sum dignus; ut intres sub tectum meum, sed tantum dic verbo, &amp; sanabitur anima mea.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Sumit reverenter ambas partes Hostiae.</stage>
                  <p>COrpus Domini nostri Jesu Christi cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stodiat animam meam in vitam ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternam. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Calicem accipiens, dicit:</stage>
                  <p>QUid retribuam Domino pro omnibus quae retribuit mihi?</p>
                  <p>Calicem salutaris accipiam, &amp; nomen Domini invocabo.</p>
                  <p>Laudans invocabo Dominum, &amp; ab inimicis meis salvus ero.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Sumit totum Sanguinem cum particula, &amp; dicit:</stage>
                  <p>SAnguis Domini nostri Jesu Christi, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stodiat animam meam in vitam aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:63525:33"/>
                  <stage>Sumens primam Ablutionem, dicit:</stage>
                  <p>QUod ore sumpsimus, Domine, puta mente capiamus, &amp; de munere tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porali fiat nobis remedium sempiter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurn.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Sumens secundam Ablutionem, dicit:</stage>
                  <p>COrpus tuum, Domine, quod sumpsi, &amp; sanguis quem potavi, adhaereat visceribus meis; &amp; praesta, ut in me non remaneat scelerum macula, quem pura &amp; sancta refecerunt Sacramenta. Qui vivis &amp; regnas in saecula saeculorum. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Digitos, Os, Calicem extergit, deinde prosequitur Missam.</stage>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="prayer">
                              <head>Communio.</head>
                              <p>BEnedicimus Deum coeli, &amp; coram omnibus viventibus confitebimur ei: quia fecit nobiscum misericordiam suam.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Dominus vobiscum:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Et cum Spiritu tuo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:63525:116"/>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="prayer">
                              <head>Postcommunio.</head>
                              <p>PRoficiat nobis ad salutem corporis &amp; animae, Domine Deus noster, hujus Sacramenti susceptio: &amp; sempiternae Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis, ejusdemque individuae Vnitatis confessio. Per Dominum nostrum Iesum Christum.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Dominus vobiscum.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Et cum Spiritu tuo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Ite, Missa est. <hi>seu.</hi> Benedicamus Domino.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Deo gratias.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Celebrans dicit pro Missae qualitate, vel <hi>Ite Missa est,</hi> vel <hi>Benedicamus Domino.</hi> In Missis Defunctorum dicit, <hi>Requiescant in pace.</hi> R. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>PLaceat tibi, sancta Trinitas, obse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium servitutis meae, &amp; praesta, ut Sacrificium quod oculis tuae Majestatis indignus obtuli, tibi sit acceptabile, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hique,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63525:117"/> &amp; omnibus pro quibus illud ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuli, sit, te miserante, propitiabile. Per Christum Dominum nostrum. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Versus ad populum, dicit:</stage>
                  <p>BEnedicat vos omnipotens Deus, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; Filius, &amp; Spiritus Sanctus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>In Missis Defunctorum non datur Benedictio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Dominus vobiscum.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Et cum Spiritu tuo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Sequentia sancti Evangelii, secundum Joannem.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Gloria tibi Domine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>IN principio erat Verbum, &amp; Verbum erat apud Deum: &amp; Deus erat Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum: hoc erat in principio apud De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Omnia per ipsum facta sunt, &amp; sine ipso factum est nihil, quod factum est, in ipso vita erat: &amp; vita erat lux ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum: &amp; lux in tenebris lucet, &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrae eam non comprehenderunt. Fuit homo missus a Deo, qui nomen erat
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:63525:34"/> Joannes. Hic venit in testimonium, ut testimonium perhiberet de lumine: ut omnes crederent per illum. Non erat ille lux; sed ut testimonium perhibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret de lumine. Erat lux vera quae illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat omnem hominem venientem in hunc Mundum. In Mundo erat, &amp; Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus per ipsum factus est, &amp; Mundus eum non cognovit. In propria venit, &amp; sui eum non receperunt. Quotquot autem receperunt eum, dedit eis potestatem fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios Dei fieri: his, qui credunt in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ejus, qui non ex sanguinibus, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ex voluntate carnis, neque ex vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate viri; sed ex Deo nati sunt. ET VERBUM CARO FAC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TUM EST; &amp; habitavit in nobis, &amp; vidimus gloriam ejus, gloriam quasi Unigeniti à Patre, plenum gratiae &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Deo gratias.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Signans Librum &amp; se, legit Evangelium se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Joannem, vel aliud Evangelium secundum Rubricas. Cum dicit, <hi>Et ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum caro factum est,</hi> genuflectit.</stage>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63525:8"/>
            <head>THE HOLY MASS.</head>
            <sp>
               <stage>The Priest at the foot of the Altar, saith:</stage>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>I will present my self at the Altar of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>The People answer.</stage>
               <p>I will approach to God, who rejoyceth my youth.</p>
            </sp>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="Psalm">
                        <head>Psalm 42.</head>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>P.</speaker>
                           <p>JƲdge me, my God, and separate my cause from that of the wicked: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me from the Man that is wicked and full of deceit.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>R.</speaker>
                           <p>Why doest thou reject me, O my God? since that thou art my strength; and why must I pass my life in sadness whil'st an Enemy afflicts me?</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>P.</speaker>
                           <p>Send me thy light and thy truth: they will lead me to thy holy Mountain and in thy Tabernacle.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63525:9"/>
                           <speaker>R.</speaker>
                           <p>And I will present my self to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of God: I will approach to God who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth my youth.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>P.</speaker>
                           <p>My God, my God, I will sing thy praises upon the Harp: why then art thou sad my Soul, and why doest thou trouble me?</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>R.</speaker>
                           <p>Hope in God; for I will praise him alwayes; because he is my God, whom I look upon as the only hopes of my Salvation.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>P.</speaker>
                           <p>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghost.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>R.</speaker>
                           <p>As it was from the beginning, so be it now, and alwayes, and in all ages. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <stage>In Masses for the Dead, and in those from Passion Sunday till Easter, the Priest having said, <hi>In nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Patris, &amp;c.</hi> begins here:</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> will present my self at the Altar of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>I will approach to God who rejoyceth my youth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>May our help be in the Name of our Lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>Who made Heaven and Earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>The Priest sayes:</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I confess to Almighty God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>Almighty God be merciful to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63525:10"/> thee, forgive thee thy sins, and bring thee to everlasting life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>I confess to Almighty God, to the blessed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> to the blessed <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel, to the blessed <hi>John Baptist,</hi> to the Holy Apostles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> to all the Saints, and to you Father, that I have sinned in thought, word, and deed: through my fault, through my fault, through my most grievous fault. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do beseech the blessed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the blessed <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel, the blessed <hi>John Baptist,</hi> the Holy Apostles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and all the Saints, and you Father, to pray for me to our Lord God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Almighty God be merciful to you, and having forgiven you your Sins, bring you to Life everlasting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Almighty and most Merciful Lord grant you Pardon, Absolution, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of your Sins.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Lord, if thou vouchsafe to turn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, thou wilt revive us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>And thy People will rejoyce in thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Lord shew us thy mercy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>And give us thy Salvation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:63525:11"/>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Lord, hear my Prayer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>And let my Voice come unto thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Our Lord be with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>And with thy Spirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>While the Priest is going up to the Altar, he sayes:</stage>
               <p>Take away from us our iniquities, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee, O Lord: that we may enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Sanctuary with a clean heart: Through <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>When the Priest is come up to the Altar, bowing down, he sayes:</stage>
               <p>We beseech thee, O Lord, by the Merits of thy Saints, whose Relicks are here, and of all the Saints, to forgive me my Sins. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:63525:12"/>
               <head>THE MASS OF THE B. TRINITY.</head>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="introit">
                           <head>The Introit.</head>
                           <p>BLessed be the Holy Trinity, and the individed Vnity of God. We will glorify him, because he hath dealt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully with us. <hi>Psal 8.</hi> O God, our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lord, how wonderful is thy Name over the whole Earth. <hi>V.</hi> Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghost, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord have mercy upon us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord have mercy upon us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord have mercy upon us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Christ have mercy upon us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Christ have mercy upon us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Christ have mercy upon us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord have mercy upon us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord have mercy upon us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord have mercy upon us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Next follows the <hi>Gloria in Excelsis,</hi> which is not said in Masses for the Dead, nor in Lent, except on Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63525:13"/> dayes, nor at Votive Masses, nor Vigils, unless it be that of Angels, and that of our B. Lady on Saturdays.</stage>
                  <p>GLory to God in the highest Heaven, Peace on Earth to Men of good will. We praise thee. We bless thee. We adore thee, We glorify thee. We give thee thanks in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to thy infinit Glory. O Lord God, King of Heaven, O God Father Almighty, O Lord only Son of God <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> O Lord God, Lamb of God, Son of the Father, who blottest out the Sins of the World, have mercy on us. O thou who takest away the Sins of the World, receive our Prayers. O thou who sittest at the right hand of thy Father, have mercy on us. For thou, O <hi>Jesus,</hi> the only Holy, the only Lord, the only most High, art altogether with the Holy Ghost, in the Glory of God the Father. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>The Priest turning towards the People, sayes:</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Lord be with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>And with thy Spirit.</p>
               </sp>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>The Prayer or Collect.</head>
                           <p>ETernal and Almighty God, who by the light of Faith hast made known to thy servants the glory of the eternal Trinity, to adore therein the Vnity of thy Soveraign Nature; grant, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63525:14"/> thee, that by the stedfastness of the same Faith we may be alwaies for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified against all adversities, through <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="lesson">
                           <head>The Lesson out of the Epistle of <hi>Paul</hi> the Blessed Apostle, to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Chap. 13.</head>
                           <p>BRethren, be cheerful, be perfect, be comforted, be all of the same mind, live in peace. And the God of peace and of love will be with you. May the grace of our Lord <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> the charity of God, and the communication of the Holy Ghost be with you all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>The Gradual.</hi> Blessed be thou, O Lord, who sittest above the Cherubim, from whence thou lookest into the bottomless depths.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>V.</hi> Lord thou art blessed in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Heaven, and thou art worthy of praise forever. <hi>Alleluja, alleluja.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>V.</hi> O Lord the God of our Fathers, thou art blessed and worthy of praise in all ages. <hi>Alleluja.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>The Prayer before the Gospel.</head>
                           <p>CLeanse my heart and lips, O Almighty God, who didst cleanse the lips of the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> with a burning coal: vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe through thy gracious Mercy so to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63525:15"/> me, that I may worthily anounce thy Holy Gospel: Through our Lord <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi> Amen. Bless me, O Lord.</p>
                           <p>Our Lord be in my heart and in my lips, that I may worthily and competently publish his Gospel. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Lord be with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>And with thy Spirit.</p>
               </sp>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="reading">
                           <head>The following part of the Gospel, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to S. <hi>John,</hi> Chap. 15.</head>
                           <p>IN those daies, <hi>Christ</hi> said to his Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: When the Comforter, whom I will send to you from the Father, shall come, being the Spirit of Truth who procéeds from the Father; he will give testimony of me, and your selves shall be witness thereof, because you have béen with me from the beginning. I have told you these things, that you be not scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized when they come. They will vanish you out of their méetings. But the time is come in which he that shall cause your death, will believe he performs a very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable service to God. And thus they will abuse you, because they know not my Father, nor me. This then I tell you, that when the time shall come, you may remember what I foretold you.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Praise be to thee, O Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:63525:16"/> Then the Priest sayes in a low voice:</stage>
                  <p>May our Sins be blotted out by the word of the Gospel. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Next is said the <hi>Creed,</hi> when it ought to be said:</stage>
                  <p>I Believe in one God the Father Almighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth, and of all Things visible and invisible.</p>
                  <p>And in one Lord <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> the only begotten Son of God, and born of the Father before all ages. God of God, Light of Light, true God of the true God: begotten, not made, consubstantial to the Father, by whom all things were made.</p>
                  <p>Who descended from Heaven, for us men, and for our salvation: and taking flesh of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> by the operation of the Holy Ghost, <hi>BECAME MAN.</hi> He also was crucified for us under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> suffered and was buried, and rose again the third day, according to the Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>Who ascended into Heaven, and sets at the right hand of the Father.</p>
                  <p>Who will come again in glory, to judge the living and the dead, of whose Kingdom there shall be no end.</p>
                  <p>And I believe in the Holy Ghost, the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63525:17"/> Lord and Giver of Life, who proceeds from the Father and the Son. Who is adored &amp; glorified jointly with the Father and the Son, who spake by the Prophets.</p>
                  <p>I believe one Holy, Catholick, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolick Church. I confess one Baptism for the Remission of Sins. I expect the Resurrection of the Dead, and Life in the World to come. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Lord be with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>And with thy Spirit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Let us Pray.</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Offertory.</hi> Blessed be God the Father, and the only Son of God, as also the Holy Ghost, <hi>one only God,</hi> who hath dealt mercifully with us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>The Priest offering up the Host, sayes.</stage>
                  <p>REceive O Holy Father, Almighty and eternal God, this unspotted Host, which I thy unworthy Servant Offer thee my living and true God, for my innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sins, offences, and negligences: for all here present, and for all faithful Christians living and dead, that it may avail me, and them to life everlasting: <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:63525:18"/>
                  <stage>When the Priest puts the Wine and the Water into the Chalice.</stage>
                  <p>O God who as a wonderful effect of thy Power, hast created Humane Nature, and restored it by a greater Miracle: Grant us by the mystery of this Wine and Water, to partake of his Divinity, who vouchsafed to take upon him our Humanity, namely <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> our Lord thy Son, who being God, liveth and reigneth with thee, in the unity of the Holy Ghost for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>When he Offers the Chalice in the midst of the Altar.</stage>
                  <p>WE offer unto thee O Lord, this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Salvation, beseeching thy Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, that it may ascend before thy Divine Majesty as a sweet perfume for our salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for that of the whole World. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>The Priest bowing, sayes:</stage>
                  <p>WE present our selves before thee with an humble and contrite spirit. O Lord accept of us and grant, that this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice may be made agreeable this day unto thee, O Lord God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>In Blessing the Bread and the Wine, he sayes.</stage>
                  <p>COme thou Almighty, and Eternal God, the Sanctifyer, and bless this Sacrifice, prepared for the glory of thy Holy Name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:63525:19"/>
                  <stage>Whilst he washeth his hands, he saies:</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Will wash my hands antong the Innocent, and I will surround thy altar, O Lord.</p>
                  <p>That I may hear the voice of praise, and declare thy mervaillous works.</p>
                  <p>Lord I have loved the Beauty of thy house, and the place of residence of thy glory.</p>
                  <p>Destroy not my Soul with the impious, nor my life with Men of blood.</p>
                  <p>Whose hands are full of iniquity, and loaded with gifts.</p>
                  <p>As for me, I have entred in my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency: redeem me, and have mercy on me.</p>
                  <p>My foot hath stood in the right way, in Churches I will bless thee, O Lord.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> is not said in Masses for the Dead, nor from Passion Sunday, till <hi>Easter.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <stage>The Priest having washed his hands, bows down at the middle of the Altar, and sayes;</stage>
                  <p>REceive, O Holy Trinity, this Oblation, which we make in memory of the Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, Resurrection, and Ascension of our Lord <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi> And in honour of the ever bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> of St. <hi>John Baptist,</hi> of the holy Apostles <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and of all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63525:20"/> the Saints, that it may be available to their honour, and to our salvation. And may they (whose memory we celebrate on Earth) vouchsafe to intercede for us in Heaven. Through <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Turning himself towards the People, he sayes;</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PRay (Brethren) that my Sacrifice, which is also yours, may be acceptable to God the Father Almighty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>To whom the People answer;</stage>
                  <p>MAy the Lord receive from thy hands, this Sacrifice to the glory and honour of his name, for our particular benefit, and for the benefit of the whole Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>The Secret Prayer.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>LOrd, who art our God, sanctifie, we beséech thée, by the Invocation of thy Name, the Host of this Oblation, &amp; make us thereby a Gift, worthy to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to thée for ever. Through Christ our Lord thy Son, who being God livech and reigneth with thée in the unity of the Holy Ghost.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <stage>This Prayer always endeth, with the ensuing words, <hi>For ever,</hi> &amp;c. which the Priest sayes aloud.</stage>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63525:21"/>
               <head>THE COMMON PREFACE.</head>
               <p>FOr ever and ever.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Our Lord be with you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And with thy Spirit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lift up your hearts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We have them lifted up to our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let us give thanks to our Lord God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is meet and just.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>IT is verily meet, and just, right, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable to salvation, that we alwaies and in all places give thanks to thee, Lord and holy Father, Almighty and eternal God, through Christ our Lord: by whom the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels praise thy Majesty, the Dominations adore it, the Powers tremble before it. The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and the Heavenly Vertues, with the Blessed Seraphins, joyntly glorify thee with exultation: Together with whom we beseech thee to admit also our praises, with humble submission, saying:</p>
               <p>Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Sabbaoth. The Heavens and Earth are full of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Hosanna</hi> in the Highest. Blessed is he
<pb facs="tcp:63525:22"/> that comes in the Name of the Lord. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanna</hi> in the Highest.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="preface">
                           <head>The Preface of the Blessed Trinity.</head>
                           <p>IT is verily méet, and just, right, and available to salvation, that we all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, and in all places, give thanks to thée, O Lord and Holy Father, Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Eternal God. Who together with thy only Son and the Holy Ghost, art one God, one Lord, not in the singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity of Persons, but in the Trinity of the same substance. For what we believe of thy Glory, as thou hast revealed it to us, the same do we believe of thy Son, and of the Holy Ghost, without diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or distinction. That in the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the true and eternal Deity, both propriety in Persons, and unity in Essence, and Equality in Glory be ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Which is celebrated by the praises of the Angels and Archangels, as also of the Cherubins and Seraphins, who cease not to crie dayly with one voice, saying: Holy, Holy, Holy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:63525:23"/>
               <head>✚ THE CANON OF THE MASS.</head>
               <p>THerefore, most mercifull Father, we humbly beseech thee through thy Son <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> our Lord, to accept and bless these ✚ Gifts, these ✚ Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents, these ✚ unspotted Sacrifices, which in the first place we offer unto thee for thy Holy Catholick Church, that thou wouldst be pleased to grant her peace, to preserve her, to unite her, and to govern her through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World; together with thy servant Pope <hi>N.</hi> our Bishop <hi>N.</hi> &amp; our King <hi>N.</hi> as also with all Orthodox believers, and observers of the Catholick and Apostolical Faith.</p>
               <sp>
                  <stage>A Commemoration for the Living.</stage>
                  <p>Be mindful, O Lord, of all thy servants, Men and Women <hi>N.</hi> and <hi>N.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Here are mentioned the Living, who are pray'd for in particular.</stage>
                  <p>And of all those especially that are here
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63525:24"/> present, whose faith and devotion is known unto thee, for whom we offer, or who offer up to thee this Sacrifice of praise for themselves, and for all theirs, for the Redemption of their souls, for the hope of their salvation, and pay their vows unto thee, the Eternal, Living and True God.</p>
                  <p>Being made partakers of the same Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and honouring the memory, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the ever glorious Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord God <hi>Jesus Christ;</hi> as also of thy blessed Apostles and Martyrs, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul, Andrew, James, John, Phillip, Bartholomew, Matthew, Simon</hi> &amp; <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus, Linus, Cletus, Clement, Xystus, Cornelius, Cyprian, Laurence, Chryse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonus, John</hi> and <hi>Paul, Cosmas</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian,</hi> and of all thy Saints, by whose merits and prayers, grant that we may in all things be strenghtned by the help of thy protection. Through the same Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>The Priest extending his hands over the Oblations, sayes:</stage>
                  <p>WE therefore beseech thee, O Lord, graciously to accept this Oblation of our servitude, and of thy whole Family;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63525:25"/> to dispose our dayes in thy peace, to preserve us from eternal damnation, and to rank us in the number of thy Elect. Through Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
                  <p>Which Oblation, we beseech thee, O God, to render in all things blessed, approved, effectual, reasonable, and acceptable, that it may be made for us, the Body and Blood of thy most. Beloved Son our Lord <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Who the day before he suffer'd, took bread into his holy and venerable hands, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lifted up his eyes towards Heaven to thee, O God, his Omnipotent Father, giving thanks to thee, he blessed it, and gave it to his Disciples, saying, Take and eat you all of this, FOR THIS IS MY BODY.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Here the Priest elevates the Sacred Host.</stage>
                  <p>In like manner, after he had supp'd, taking this excellent Chalice into his holy and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable hands, giving thee also thanks, he blessed it, and gave it to his Disciples, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Take and drink you all of this, FOR THIS IS THE CHALICE OF MY BLOƲD, of the New and Everlasting Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63525:26"/> (a Mystery of Faith,) which shall be shed for you, and for many, to the remis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Sins.</p>
                  <p>As often as you do these things, you shall do them in memory of me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Here the Priest holds up the Chalice.</stage>
                  <p>WHerefore, O Lord, we thy Servants and thy holy People, being mindfull both of the blessed Passion of the same Christ thy Son our Lord, and of his Resurrection, as also of his glorious Ascension into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, offer unto thy most excellent Majesty, of thy Gifts and Grants a pure Host, an Holy Host, an Immaculate Host, the holy Bread of eternal life, and Chalice of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal salvation.</p>
                  <p>Ʋpon which we beseech thee to look with a propitious and serene countenance, and to accept them as thou wert pleased graciously to accept the gifts of thy Servant <hi>Abel</hi> the just, and the Sacrifice of our Patriarck <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> and the Holy Sacrifice and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spotted Host which thy High Priest <hi>Melchiy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedeck</hi> offered to thee.</p>
                  <p>We most humbly beseech thee, Almighty God, command these things to be carried by the hands of thy Holy Angel unto thy High Altar, in the presence of thy Divine
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63525:27"/> Majesty, that as many of us as have by this participation of the Altar, taken the most sacred Body and Bloud of thy Son, may be replenished with all Heavenly grace and benediction. Through the same Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>The Commemoration for the Dead.</stage>
                  <p>BE mindful also, O Lord, of thy servants, Men and Women <hi>N.</hi> and <hi>N.</hi> who have gone before us with the sign of Faith, and rest in the sleep of peace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Here are mentioned such Dead, as are pray'd for in particular.</stage>
                  <p>We beseech thee, O Lord, that thou grant to them and to all that rest in Christ, a place of refreshment, light and peace. Through the same Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>The Priest knocking his brest, sayes:</stage>
                  <p>ANd to us sinners thy servants, hoping in the multitude of thy mercies, vouchsafe to grant some part and society with thy holy Apostles and Martyrs, with John, Stephen, Matthias, Barnaby, Ignatius,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63525:28"/> Alexander, Marcellinus, Peter, Felicitas, Perpetua, Agatha, Lucia, Agnes, Cecilia, Anastafia, and with all thy Saints: into the Company of whom we humbly beseech thee to admit us, not upon the accompt of our merit, but of thy forwardness to pardon us. Through Christ our Lord.</p>
                  <p>By whom, O Lord, thou doest ever effect all these Blessings, thou sanctifiest, thou quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, thou blessest and bestowest upon us. By him, and with him, and in him, to thee, O God the Father Almighty, all honour and glory is due, in the unity of the Holy Ghost. For ever and ever. <hi>Resp.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Let us pray.</stage>
                  <p>BEing instructed by wholsom precepts, and following the form of the divine Institution, we presume to say:</p>
                  <p>Our Father, who art in Heaven, Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be thy Name, Thy Kingdom come, Thy will be done on Earth, as it is in Heaven: Give us this day our dayly Bread, And forgive us our debts, as we forgive our debtors. And lead us not into temptation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
                  <p>But deliver us from evil.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:63525:29"/>
                  <p>Deliver us we beseech thee, O Lord, from all evills past, present and to come: and by the Intercession of the Blessed and ever glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Virgin Mary Mother of God, and of thy holy Apostles Peter and Paul, Andrew, and all the Saints: grant bountifully unto us peace in our dayes, that through the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of thy mercies, we may be alwaies free from sin, and secured from all distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance. Through our same Lord Jesus Christ thy Son, who being God, liveth and reigneth with thee in the unity of the Holy Ghost; world without end.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>The peace of our Lord be alwaies with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Resp.</speaker>
                  <p>And with thy Spirit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>The Priest putting one part of the Sacred Host into the Chalice, sayes:</stage>
                  <p>MAy this Commixtion and Consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Body and Bloud of our Lord Jesus Christ, be to us that receive it, effectual to eternal life. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Then he sayes, knocking his brest thrice:</stage>
                  <p>LAmb of God, who takest away the sins of the world, have mercy on us:</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:63525:30"/>
                  <p>Lamb of God, who takest away the sins of the world, have mercy on us.</p>
                  <p>Lamb of God, who takest away the sins of the world, grant us peace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>In Masses for the Dead, instead of say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twice <hi>Have mercy on us,</hi> 'tis twice said, <hi>Give them rest;</hi> and instead of saying, <hi>Grant us peace,</hi> 'tis said, <hi>Grant them everlasting rest.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>O Lord Jesus Christ, who saidst to thy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, I leave you peace, I give you my peace; look not on my sins, but on the Faith of thy Church; vouchsafe her such peace and union, as may be agreable to thy will: Who livest and reignest, for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>The fore-mentioned Prayer is omitted in Masses for the Dead.</stage>
                  <p>O Lord Jesus Christ, Son of the living God, who according to the will of the Father, hast by thy Death given life to the World, through the co-operation of the Holy Ghost; deliver me by this thy most sacred Body and Bloud, from all my iniquities, and from all evills. Make me alwaies obedient to thy Commandments, and never suffer me
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63525:31"/> to be separated from thee: who together with the same Father and the Holy Ghost, livest and reignest God, world without end. Amen.</p>
                  <p>GRant, O Lord Jesus Christ, that this participation of thy Body, which I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily presume to receive, may not turn to my judgment and condemnation; but may, through thy mercy, be available to the cure and safe-guard of my soul and body: who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, livest and reignest with God the Father, in the unity of the Holy Ghost, for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Taking in his hands the sacred Host, he sayes:</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Will take this Heavenly Bread, and will call upon the name of the Lord:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>He knocks his breast, saying humbly and devoutly.</stage>
                  <p>LOrd, I am not worthy, that thou shouldst enter under my roof; say but the word, and my soul shall be cured.</p>
                  <p>Lord, I am not worthy, that thou shouldst enter under my roof; say but the word, and my soul shall be cured.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:63525:32"/>
                  <p>Lord, I am not worthy that thou shouldst enter under my roof, say but the word, and my soul shall be cured.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Receiving the Body of Christ:</stage>
                  <p>THe Body of our Lord <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve my soul to everlasting Life. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Taking the <hi>Chalice,</hi> he sayes:</stage>
                  <p>WHat return shall I make to our Lord for all the benefits he hath afforded me?</p>
                  <p>I will take the <hi>Chalice</hi> of salvation, and will call upon the name of our Lord.</p>
                  <p>I will call upon our Lord in praising him, and I shall be safe from my enemies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Receiving the Bloud of our Saviour, he sayes:</stage>
                  <p>THe Bloud of our Lord <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> preserve my soul to Life everlasting. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:63525:115"/>
                  <stage>Taking the first Ablution, or Wine in the <hi>Chalice,</hi> he sayes:</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GRant, O Lord, that what we have t<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e with our Mouth, we may receive with a pure Mind, and that it may of a temporal Gift, become to us an Everlasting Remedy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>Taking the second Ablution, he sayes:</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAY thy Body which I have received, O Lord, and thy Blood which I have drank, eleave unto my Bowels; and grant, that no stain of Sin may remain in me; whom thy pure and holy Sacraments have fed. Who livest and reignest for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>He wipes his Mouth, his Fingers, and the Chalice; and then continues the Mass.</stage>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="prayer">
                              <head>The Communion.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>WE bless the God of Heaven, and will acknowledge him in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sente of the whole World, because he hath shewn to us his mercy.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Lord be with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>And with thy Spirit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:63525:116"/>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="prayer">
                              <head>The Post-Communion.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>O Lord our God, grant, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of this holy Sacrament, and the confession of the sempiternal Trinity, and the indivisible Vnity of the same, may avail us to the Salvation of Body and Soul. Through Christ our Lord.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Lord be with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>And with thy Spirit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Depart, <hi>Mass</hi> is done, <hi>or,</hi> Bless we our Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Thanks be to God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>If <hi>Gloria in excelsis</hi> hath not been said, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of <hi>Ite Missa est,</hi> is said, <hi>Benedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Domino, Bless we our Lord.</hi> And in Masses for the Dead, <hi>Requiescant in pace, May they rest in Peace:</hi> To which is answered, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>O Holy <hi>Trinity,</hi> may the Obedience of my Servitude be pleasing to thee; and grant, that the Sacrifice, which I, though unworthy, have offered in the Sight of thy Majesty, may be acceptable unto thee: And
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63525:33"/> that by thy mercy, it may be propitiatory to my self, and to all those for whom I have offered it. Through <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>The Priest turning himself towards the People, sayes:</stage>
                  <p>THe Almighty God, Father, Son, and Holy Ghost bless you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>In Masses for the Dead, the Benediction is not given.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Lord be with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>And with thy Spirit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>The beginning of the holy Gospel, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to St. <hi>John.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R.</speaker>
                  <p>Glory be to our Lord.</p>
                  <p>IN the beginning was the word, and the word was with God, and the word was God. The same was in the beginning with God. All things were made by him, and without him was made nothing, that was made, in him was life, and the life was the light of Men. And the light shined in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and darkness did not comprehend it. There was a Man sent from God, whose
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63525:34"/> name was <hi>John.</hi> He came for a witness, to give testimony of the light, that by him all might believe. He was not the light, but to give testimony of the light. He was the true light that enlightens every Man that comes into this World. He was in the World, and the World was made by him, and the World knew him not. He came to his own, and his own received him not. But as many as received him, he gave them power to be made the Sons of God, those who believe in his name, who are born not of bloud, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of Man; but of God. AND THE WORD WAS MADE FLESH, and dwelt among us, and we saw his glory, as the glory of the only begotten of the Father, full of grace and verity. <hi>R.</hi> Thanks be to God.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>St. <hi>John</hi>'s Gospel is alwaies said at the end of <hi>Mass,</hi> unless it be when a Double Feast is said that falls upon a Sunday; or on a Week day, that hath a proper Gospel.</stage>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:63525:35"/>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:63525:35"/>
            <head>THE HOLY SACRIFICE OF THE MASS EXPOUNDED in general.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. The words <hi>Sacrifice</hi> and <hi>Mass</hi> Explained.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S every one knows, that true Religion is a religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship pay'd to the Soveraign Being, which is God: So likewise all the World is assured, that this Worship con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists chiefly in Sacrifice, as the Soveraign homage due only to God. Therefore it
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:63525:36"/> is our main concern to understand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right these two Words, <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> and <hi>Mass.</hi> For, as <hi>Epictetus</hi> sayes, <hi>The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of knowledg, is to frame a right notion of the words, Ap. Arian. l. 2. c.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>The word <hi>Sacrifice</hi> hath a large signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; and generally speaking, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies all the Duties of Man towards God, as St. <hi>Augustin</hi> tells us; <hi>Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium est omne opus quod agitur, ut sancta societate inhaereamus Deo: lib. 10. de Civ. Dei c.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>And these Duties relate either to the Soul, to the Body, or to our Fortune: <hi>David,</hi> for Example, calls an Act of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition a Sacrifice: <hi>Sacrificium Deo spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus contribulatus. Psalm.</hi> 50. 19. The Duties of the Body, even the very lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of our hands towards Heaven, he terms a Sacrifice: <hi>Elevatio manuum mearum sacrificium vespertinum. Ps.</hi> 140. 2. Alms, as a part of Man's Estate and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, is a Sacrifice in St. <hi>Austin</hi>'s judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>Sacrificium Christiani, est eleemo. syna: in pauperem. Lib. 50. Homiliarum Homil. 29. c.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>But all these are improperly said to be Sacrifices; and we may say with <hi>Isaac, Where is the Victim? Gen.</hi> 22. 7. For
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:63525:36"/>
                  <hi>to sacrifice,</hi> signifies properly in <hi>Hebrew, Greek, Latine, English, &amp;c.</hi> to kill and destroy; as the bulls and goats were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed in the Old Law: And in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral consent of all Divines, the word <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> signifies, <hi>A visible thing offer'd to God only, by a lawfull Priest, where some real change is made in the thing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered.</hi> In this Definition are obscurely comprehended several things, which we shall explain at length; <hi>viz.</hi> The end for which the Sacrifices are offered, the victim, the Priest, the Altar, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ceremonies, and the inward dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of the Assistants.</p>
               <p>Now, as for the word <hi>Mass,</hi> it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the verb <hi>mitto;</hi> for the word <hi>missa,</hi> is the very same as <hi>missio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to understand this, we must know, that when the <hi>Latine</hi> Tongue began to be corrupted at the decay of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> the <hi>Latines</hi> used often to say, <hi>missa</hi> for <hi>missio,</hi> which signifies <hi>sending.</hi> And the word <hi>remissa</hi> for <hi>remissio,</hi> is often to be found among the Writers of those times; <hi>Diximus de remissa peccatorum,</hi> saith <hi>Tertulian. lib. 4. advers. Marcion. cap.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Mass</hi> then is thus named, from
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63525:37"/> the noblest part of the Sacrifice, which is the <hi>Holocaustial</hi> part, <hi>page</hi> 42. where, at the words, <hi>Per quem haec, Domine, &amp;c.</hi> we publickly acknowledge, that God the Father <hi>sends</hi> us all his Blessings and favours by <hi>Christ</hi> our Mediator, and his Messenger; and at the same time, we <hi>send</hi> back to him our gratitude and Thanksgiving for them, by the same <hi>Christ,</hi> and in <hi>Christ,</hi> and with <hi>Christ,</hi> saying, <hi>Per ipsum, &amp; cum ipso, &amp; in ipso, sit—omnis honor &amp; glorie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. Of the ends for which Men offer Sacrifices.</head>
               <p>SAcrifice being a Divine worship, and the first duty the Creature ows to his Creator, it engageth him as soon as he proceeds out of nothing, to acknowledg his Original by a solemn ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, in professing publickly, that he hath received his being from him; and that he is unworthy to appear in his presence. And though all Gods perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions may justly challenge this homage
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:63525:37"/> yet one of them chiefly obliges us to that duty.</p>
               <p>That is the Soveraignty he hath over his Creature. For he depends on him both in Creation and preservation. He hath no right to exist before he issued from nothing; and being not yet in Nature, could have no pretensious of aspiring either to Grace or Glory. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now brought from <hi>Non-Entity,</hi> he depends still upon his Soveraign, nor could he be able to subsist one moment without assistance from him. Now his Preservation, is a consequence of his Creation. The same Power that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth him preserves him; for let but God cease to preserve him, and he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly moulders into nothing. Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency therefore and servitude, make one part of his Essence. And this was the first motive that invited Man to offer up Sacrifices, as a publick acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods Power.</p>
               <p>But since we revolted against God by the sin of <hi>Adam,</hi> we are forced to offer Sacrifice to his offended Justice. First to pacify his wrath drawn upon us by our pride and ingratitude. Next to acknowledge the dependency we have
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:63525:38"/> of him, to do the good we are bound to perform, and so continually to beg for the succour of his Grace: So that here are four sorts of Actions, which in the condition we are in, ought to be the continual employment of our life; <hi>viz.</hi> To honour God like a God; to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy his Justice; to thank him for his Benefits; to implore his assistance, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the necessity we have of it. These four Duties God commanded the <hi>Jews</hi> by the mouth of his Servant <hi>Moses</hi> to perform, in offering up to him four sorts of Sacrifices.</p>
               <p>The first was the <hi>Holocaust,</hi> where the <hi>Victim</hi> was wholly consumed by fire. The second was the <hi>Victim</hi> of Expiation or Atonement for sin. The third and fourth were called <hi>Peace-Offerings,</hi> of which the one was offered in Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving for some Benefit received, and in sign of a joyful union and friendly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondence between the Creator and the Creature; and the other to obtain some new favours.</p>
               <p>God then was to be honoured by a Sacrifice, because it is the worship which is proper to him, and due to him alone. But it was requisite, the <hi>Victim</hi> should
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:63525:38"/> be worthy of his Divine Majesty, which Bulls and Goats were not. And conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, it must be the noblest of his Creatures; that is to say, <hi>Man,</hi> who could worship him in a reasonable, free, and holy manner, as <hi>Adam</hi> did before his fall. But in regard that since his fall, Man is defiled by sin, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently is unworthy to be the <hi>Victim;</hi> and to be offered to him, God makes the second Person of the <hi>Trinity</hi> to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume our humane Nature, that by this means, being vested with a Body, he might instead of defiled Man, become a pure ad immaculate <hi>Victim;</hi> not only comprehending in one, but transcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all those of the <hi>Old Law;</hi> thereby to honour God the Father, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile us to him by his Holiness and Innocency, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:63525:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. Of Sacrifices in general.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Austin</hi> teaches excellently well, that there can be no true Religion without a Sacrifice; because Religion is nothing but the worship of God, and the Soveraign worship due to him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists chiefly in Sacrifice; wherefore there must needs be a Sacrifice in the True Religion. This supposed as a clear and undoubted Truth, it will not be hard to make out, that this homage and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, is that which is offred to him on the Altar; especially when we have well considered, the conditions requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for a Sacrifice in the <hi>Old Law.</hi> We find then in Holy Scripture six main, and as it were fundamental conditions, for all the antient Sacrifices.</p>
               <p n="1">I. First, the Sanctification of the Offerers; that is, their preparation for so holy an Action, <hi>Job 1. 4. 1. Reg. 16. 5. Exod.</hi> 29. 33.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The Sanctification of the <hi>Victim;</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:63525:39"/> that is, the Preparing and making it ready for the Sacrifice, <hi>Levit.</hi> 17. 5.</p>
               <p n="3">III. The Destruction, death or kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the <hi>Victim, Levit. 4. 25, &amp;</hi> 33.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. The Oblation of the <hi>Victim,</hi> where, according to the form prescribed in the Law or taught by Tradition, it was actually offered to Gods Glory and Honour, <hi>Exod.</hi> 35. 21.</p>
               <p n="5">V. The Consummation of the <hi>Victim,</hi> which was devoured and consumed to ashes by fire, <hi>Levit. 17. 13. 17. Exod.</hi> 32. 6.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. The Communion of the <hi>Victim;</hi> which in the <hi>Peace-Offering</hi> was divided into three parts; <hi>viz.</hi> The Blood and the Fat for God. The Breast and the Shoulder for the Priest. And the rest for the People, <hi>Levit. 6 16. Deut.</hi> 16. 11.</p>
               <p>To these, Tradition adds a seventh Condition, which is a Thanksgiving the <hi>Jews</hi> made to God, after their having eaten the <hi>Paschal-Lamb,</hi> sayes <hi>Baronius, Paulus Brugenfis, Cornelius a Lapide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If then <hi>Christ</hi> be the Accomplishment of the Law, and that by acquitting us, he is oblidged to fulfill all the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures thereof; his Sacrifice must of necessity comprehend all these condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:63525:40"/> and we must find on the Altar, what we find not on the <hi>Cross.</hi> For though these two Sacrifices be one and the same thing in substance, yet they differ in their circumstances. Therefore hath <hi>Christ</hi> offered up himself in a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sacrifice, and joyned the Sacrifice of the <hi>Altar,</hi> with that of the <hi>Cross:</hi> that the one seconding the other, they might fulfill all those of the <hi>Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross</hi> being wholy devoted to God, as an <hi>Holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caust,</hi> Men had not their portion of the flesh of the <hi>Victim,</hi> as they had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law. Wherefore <hi>Christ</hi> was pleased to ordain another in the Church; where, by a wonderfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of his love, giving up himself in the same Action wholly to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and at one and the same time also to the Faithful; he has advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giously fulfilled for us all the Sacrifices of the Law.</p>
               <p>To understand then how <hi>Christians</hi> stood in need that <hi>Christ</hi> should offer up for them a double Sacrifice, in that of the <hi>Cross</hi> and of the <hi>Altar;</hi> and to understand the difference between these two, we must know; That the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:63525:40"/> of the <hi>Cross</hi> was properly speaking a Sacrifice of Redemption, and so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently universal for all the World. But the Sacrifice of the <hi>Altar</hi> is particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and for some only: That of the <hi>Cross</hi> was the general Exchequer of our Redemption; that of the <hi>Altar</hi> is the Key that opens that Treasury, and the Bucket to draw up water from the Well. On the <hi>Cross Christ</hi> offered up himself for all Men, his Love excluded no Nation, nor condition, and the most desperatly wicked might pretend to it, since the first that received the benefit thereof, were Theeves and Murderers.</p>
               <p>But the Sacrifice of the <hi>Altar</hi> is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and a Sacrifice of Religion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating only to the Faithfull that are within the pale of the Church: Its me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, though infinite, extend not to Strangers; and Excommunicated per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons are banished from it; The <hi>Mass</hi> then being a Sacrifice of Religion, it must of necessity be frequently offered; and for the continual honouring of God the Father, must continually be renewed in our Temples.</p>
               <p>This is the Sacrifice of Love repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every day, as it was figured in the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:63525:41"/> Dayly Sacrifice and continual <hi>Holocaust</hi> of the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> stiled <hi>Juge Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium.</hi> For the <hi>Jews,</hi> by Gods special command, were <hi>dayly to offer a Lamb morning and evening, with a Cake of Bread, and Wine, Exod. 29. 38. Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> 28. 3.</p>
               <p>But is this a figure, or the Thing it self? so clearly was it appointed out two thousand years before <hi>Christ</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the <hi>Mass.</hi> For what else could that <hi>Lamb</hi> offered with <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> signify, but <hi>Christ</hi> himself, (stiled by St. <hi>John 1. 29. the Lamb of God)</hi> offered under the <hi>species</hi> of Bread and Wine? The words <hi>morning</hi> and <hi>evening</hi> signify, <hi>Christ</hi> offered from the beginning to the end of the World; <hi>Agnus occisus ab origine mundi, Apoc.</hi> 13. 8.</p>
               <p>But now to come to the other main difference between the Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross,</hi> and that of the <hi>Altar:</hi> we must further know, That indeed the Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross</hi> merited all, but yet apply'd nothing: for ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral causes produce all, but apply no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and particular causes produce nothing, but apply all. An example of this we have in Nature. The <hi>Sun,</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:63525:41"/> which is a generall cause, produces no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by its self; but together with the Clouds, makes hail and snow: with the dew, brings forth herbs and flowers; with the Earth, produceth Gold and Minerals. So that the fruitfulness of this general cause must needs be apply'd, for otherwise, it produceth nothing alone.</p>
               <p>What we see in Nature, we believe in Grace. The Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross,</hi> is the General Cause and source of all Merit, Grace, and Vertue: And the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the <hi>Altar</hi> is a Particular Cause, applying to us all the Merits of the <hi>Cross,</hi> provided we prepare our selves to receive worthily at the <hi>Altar,</hi> those benefits he purchased for us on the <hi>Cross.</hi> Hence we may infer, what mutual dependency these two Sacrifices have one of another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:63525:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. The <hi>Mass</hi> defined, and divided.</head>
               <p>FROM what hath been said, we may define the <hi>Mass</hi> to be, <hi>The Great Sacrifice of the New Law, by which are applyed to us the merits of the Sacrifice of the</hi> Cross, <hi>either in a Sacramental or in a Spiritual Communion.</hi> The <hi>Mass</hi> thus defined, comprehends both a Sacrifice, and a Sacrament; and it is divided into five parts.</p>
               <p>The first, is from the <hi>Introit,</hi> to the Gospel ended: or till the Priest un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veils the Chalice.</p>
               <p>The II. is from the unveiling of the Chalice, to the <hi>Canon;</hi> or till the <hi>Clerk</hi> first rings the little Bell.</p>
               <p>The III. part is from the beginning of the <hi>Canon,</hi> to the dividing of the <hi>Sacred Host;</hi> or till the Priest hath said aloud, <hi>Pax Domini sit semper vobiscum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The IV. is from the dividing of the <hi>Sacred Host,</hi> till the <hi>Communion</hi> ended; that is, till the Priest wipes, and veiles the Chalice again.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:63525:42"/>
               <p>The V, and last is from the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> to the end of the last Gospel.</p>
               <p>Now, the first is to prepare both the Priest and the People to the great Action of the Sacrifice, by reading the Divine Scriptures, by Prayers, and by praising of God.</p>
               <p>The second is to prepare the Bread and Wine for the Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>The third is the main Action of Offering the Sacrifice; which Action is subdivided into five other parts: The first of which contains the general in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Church, in offering this Sacrifice. And this first part lasteth from the beginning of the <hi>Canon,</hi> until the Priest holds his hands over the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and the <hi>Host.</hi> The four other parts answer to the four chief Sacrifices of the <hi>Old Law; viz.</hi> That of Expiation, that of Thanksgiving, that of Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration, and that of <hi>Holocaust.</hi> All which were likewise offered at once by the <hi>Jews,</hi> on their <hi>Pentecost</hi> Solemnity, with the Oblation of <hi>the first fruits, Levit.</hi> 2. 39.</p>
               <p>The fourth part contains the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion;</hi> and the Preparations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. The fifth part is but a Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:63525:43"/> for the Blessings received in the <hi>Communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, that we may not think this Division of the <hi>Mass</hi> to be a Chimeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal invention of Man's fancy; let us examine the first Institution of it by <hi>Christ</hi> himself, and we shall find in the Scripture.</p>
               <p>First, the Preparation of the Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, in that Ceremony which <hi>Christ</hi> used, when he began to wash the feet of his Disciples, immediately before the Institution of the <hi>Eucharist, John</hi> 13. 5.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Preparation of the Bread and Wine in <hi>Christ</hi>'s <hi>Blessing and breaking</hi> them, before the Consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 26.</p>
               <p>Thirdly; the Action of the Sacrifice, in the Consecration and change of the Bread and Wine, when he said, <hi>This is my Body, Matth.</hi> 26. 26.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the <hi>Communion,</hi> when <hi>Christ</hi> said to his Disciples, <hi>Take, and cat, Matth.</hi> 26. 26.</p>
               <p>Lastly, the Thanksgiving, in these words, <hi>And when they had sung an Hymn of Thanksgiving, Matth.</hi> 26. 30.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:63525:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. Of the Priest.</head>
               <p>ALL Sacrifices suppose a Priest, by whose hands they are to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. In the Law of Nature, which lasted from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moses,</hi> every Eldest Son was a <hi>Priest;</hi> and by his Birth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to Gods service. And in the <hi>Mosaical</hi> Law, which lasted from <hi>Moses</hi> to <hi>Christ,</hi> God would likewise have all the first born Sons, dedicated to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13. 2. But in their place, he assumed to his service the <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Levi, Num.</hi> 3. 71.</p>
               <p>But in the Law of Grace, St. <hi>Peter</hi> 1 Ep. 2. 5. calls all <hi>Christians, An Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of holy Priests, who are to offer to God spiritual Sacrifices, that may be acceptable to him by Jesus Christ.</hi> To understand this rightly, we must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member; That as there are two sorts of Sacrifices, as we have distinguished before, so there are two sorts of Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. The one external and visible;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:63525:44"/> the other internal and invisible, St. <hi>Thom. secunda secundae qu. 85 a.</hi> 4. The first of these belongs to such as have been ordained to consecrate and offer at the Altar the Body and Bloud of <hi>Christ,</hi> in quality of publick Ministers. But the second is common to all the living Members of the Church. So that by the title of <hi>Christians</hi> we share in the Priesthood of <hi>Christ,</hi> of which we are made partakers in our Baptism, by the Unction of <hi>Holy Chrisma,</hi> on the Child's head.</p>
               <p>And by vertue of this Spiritual Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood it is, that in assisting at the holy Sacrifice of the <hi>Mass,</hi> we joyntly offer it with the Priest: this Sacrifice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no less ours than his. It is our <hi>Victim,</hi> it is our <hi>Oblation,</hi> which he offers with us, and we with him, and which he and we, together with the <hi>Triumphant Church,</hi> offer to God the Father by his Son.</p>
               <p>The Priests words at <hi>Orate, fratres,</hi> are an evident proof thereof, when he sayes, <hi>Pray, Brethren, that this my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, which is likewise yours, be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to Almighty God.</hi> And the words that immediately follow the first <hi>Memento</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:63525:44"/> and the Consecration, are a greater proof yet, where the Priest sayes, <hi>Be mindfull—of all those that are here present—for whom we offer, or who offer up to thee this Sacrifice, &amp;c.</hi> Nor doth the Priest say, his Host, his Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his Gifts, his Sacrifice; but, our Host, our Oblation, out Gifts, and our Sacrifice. Neither in the <hi>Canon</hi> doth he speak in the singular number, nor in his own private name, but alwaies in general, and as one deputed from the People.</p>
               <p>They had in the Old Law a figure of this Spiritual Priesthood common to all <hi>Christians.</hi> For it was commanded that the <hi>Paschal Lamb</hi> should be offered in Sacrifice, not by the Priest alone, but by all the People, <hi>Immolabit eum universa multitudo, Exod.</hi> 12. 6.</p>
               <p>If then the Prayers of the <hi>Mass</hi> are common to us with the Priest, who can doubt, but that uniting our mouthes and hearts joyntly with him, they must needs be wonderfully efficacious, for the obtaining from God the effect of our Petitions?</p>
               <p>Certainly, all <hi>Christians</hi> have an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to reflect more upon these great
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:63525:45"/> Truths, then usually they do. For their Calling is so Holy, that not only when they assist at the Sacrifice of the <hi>Mass,</hi> they are bound to perform the duty of Spiritual Priests, in offering up <hi>Christ</hi> with the Priest; but their whole Life ought to be a continual Sacrifice, in offering up themselves as <hi>Victims, holy, living, and pleasing to God, Rom.</hi> 12. 1. But for as much as humane frailty hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders this continual readiness of sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing our selves, God will have us to renew it at least, when we assist at <hi>Mass.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. Of the Victim.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Victims,</hi> or things appointed for Sacrifice, both in the Law of Nature and of <hi>Moses,</hi> were of three sorts. First, there were Beasts, as Sheep, Oxen, Turtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and these were called <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctims.</hi> Next the fruits of the Earth, as Bread, Salt, Incense, these were called <hi>Immolations.</hi> Then Liquors, as Bloud, Wine, Oyl, and these were called <hi>Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:63525:45"/> But all these are comprehended in the single <hi>Victim</hi> of the Law of Grace; <hi>viz.</hi> the true <hi>Body and Bloud of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as in the Old Law, several qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications were required in the <hi>Victim,</hi> to be presented to God; for example, to be the first born, to be of such a coulor, or of such an age: So likewise in the Law of Grace, that the <hi>Victim</hi> may be acceptable to God, it must have such and such qualifications, as are to be found together, neither in Angels, Men or beasts; but only in <hi>Christ,</hi> who alone can be the <hi>Victim</hi> of <hi>Christian</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p>First, it must be <hi>Innocent,</hi> and no way guilty of sin, of which it is the remedy. Next it must be <hi>Rational,</hi> to treat with God, and to speak in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of Man, whose cause it appears in. Thirdly, it must be <hi>Mortal,</hi> that it may undergo the punishment that sin hath deserved, and thereby sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy the Divine Justice. Lastly, and above all, it must of necessity be <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite,</hi> as is the malice of sin; that so God's honour may have a full repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Man's debt compleatly sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd.</p>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:63525:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:63525:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:63525:47"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:63525:47"/>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:63525:48"/>
               <p>But for as much as <hi>Christians</hi> are the Images of <hi>Christ,</hi> which glorious title obliges them to imitate their Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, we must sacrifice our selves as he did, and become <hi>Victims</hi> with him, as we are Priests with him. For <hi>Christ</hi> does not only offer himself here, as a <hi>Victim</hi> for us, but offers us at the same time with himself. As a Priest he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers for the whole Church, so he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise offers the whole Church together with himself. This important truth is clearly thought by the Great Saint <hi>Austin, lib. 10. de Civit. Dei cap. 6. In hoc Sacramento Fidelibus noto quod fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentat Ecclesia, hoc idem demonstratur, quod in ea Oblatione quam offert, ipsa offeratur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it follows, that when we are present at this Sacrifice of the <hi>Mass,</hi> we ought to offer up our selves, as living <hi>Victims,</hi> in imitation of young <hi>Isaac,</hi> when his hands were bound upon the Altar, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. 9. to the end we may go out more mortified, than we came in. For in all Sacrifices the <hi>Victim</hi> being dessign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be mortified, and <hi>Christ</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a condition to suffer any more; we are properly the <hi>Victims,</hi> in which
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:63525:48"/> the effect of mortification is to be found, that it may be said of every one; <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificatus carne, vivificatus autem spiritu, 1 Pet.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. Of the Altar.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NOE,</hi> as we find recorded in Holy Scripture, was the first that built and made use of Altars in the Law of Nature, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. 20. But in the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> they had two distinct Altars within the Temple; <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naim,</hi> or Incense, on which they burnt most adoriferent perfumes and Incense, both morning and evening, in the sight of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. The other was the <hi>Altar of Holocausts,</hi> whereon they burnt the <hi>Victims</hi> in Sacrifice to God, <hi>Exod. 27, and</hi> 28. And upon which, besides other votive offerings, they dayly sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crified a Lamb.</p>
               <p>To these Altars of the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and of <hi>Moses,</hi> hath succeeded that of the <hi>Christians,</hi> approved by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:63525:49"/>
                  <hi>Cor. 9. 13 Heb.</hi> 9. 13. And which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presents to us <hi>Christ;</hi> and therefore is of stone, because <hi>Christ</hi> is stiled by St. <hi>Paul, The corner stone, 1 Cor.</hi> 20. This Altar is anoynted, to signify the Uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Divine Grace; after the example of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who poured oyl on the stone he had slept upon, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. 18. and did thereby consecrate it an Altar.</p>
               <p>In like manner, this our Altar is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrated with many significant Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. And by that Consecration, the presence of the Holy Ghost being invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated upon the Altar, does by a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and invisible kind of incubation, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge it of all corruption it may have received from the Prince of the Aire, and brings it under the shadow of the <hi>Almighty;</hi> and exalting it to a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rential state of Holiness and Divinity, which intermixing with that place or stone, not by a gross adherence, but by energicall communion, induceth a nature and condition apt to quicken and assure Devotion, and disposeth the acts there done, to more illustious ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of blessings and success.</p>
               <p>But the Altar is not only the figure of <hi>Christ,</hi> but is moreover the figure
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:63525:49"/> of every <hi>Christian;</hi> seeing St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that they are <hi>the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Holy Ghost, 1 Cor.</hi> 3. 16. and St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls all <hi>Christians, the living Stones of this Building 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 5. St. <hi>Austin</hi> explaining further this truth, sayes, that our heart is the Altar of <hi>Christ: Christi est altare cor nostrum; de Civit. Dei l.</hi> 20. And the Bishop in that excellent Preface he pronounces at the Consecration of Altars, bids us sacrifice our pride and wrath upon the Altar; <hi>Sit ergo in hoc Altari innocentiae cultus; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moletur superbia, iracundia juguletur.</hi> But how? The humble <hi>Christian</hi> must sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice the proud Son of <hi>Adam.</hi> The mild Son of the second <hi>Adam,</hi> must kill the angry Son of the first <hi>Adam:</hi> For we have two Men in us; the Spiritual, and the Carnal, according to St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, the Altar represents to us the Table of the Lord, <hi>Mensa Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, Malach.</hi> 1. 7. And therefore is it spead over with a white linnin, as a Table-cloth lay'd, for the Faithfull to feast on the precious Banquet of the Sacred Body and Bloud of <hi>Christ.</hi> And indeed the Sacrifices of the Old Law were like a Feast, where God did fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:63525:50"/> converse, and as it were eat with Man, which was signified by the fire coming down from Heaven and devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Victim, Levit.</hi> 9. 24. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did God command that Bread, Meat, Wine, Oyl, and Salt should be offered to him, which are both the substance and sawces of a Feast.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. Of Ceremonies in the Offering of Sacrifices.</head>
               <p>NEVER was there any Religion without Ceremonies. The <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> had impious and superstitious ones. The <hi>Jews</hi> had carnal ones, and those both very difficult and in great number, witness the whole Book of <hi>Leviticus, &amp;c.</hi> Their <hi>Libations</hi> were offered by an effusion of the Liquors. The <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molations</hi> of the fruits of the Earth suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered some violent alteration made in them: The Bread, for example, was cut in small morsels. The Cakes were fryed or baked in an oven, or on a
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:63525:50"/> grid-iron. The Salt was burnt. The Incense fumed away in smoak. A hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Corn was burnt, and Corn was pounded. The <hi>Sacrifice of Beasts,</hi> was performed by slaughtering, offering, and burning them.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Victim</hi> of the Evangelical Law, is far from being any way bloudy; here the substance of Bread and Wine, are miraculously distroy'd, and the Body of <hi>Christ</hi> takes its place. But what is here to be admired, is, that the instrument of this voluntary, innocent, and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical slaughter of <hi>Christ,</hi> are the words of <hi>Consecration, This is my Body, &amp;c. This is my Bloud, &amp;c.</hi> Behold the sword that does the work, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently slaughters this pure, and adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Victim;</hi> mystically parting the Body from the Bloud, the Priest, <hi>Vocem adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens pro gladio,</hi> sayes St. <hi>Greg. Nazian. Ep. 240. ad Amphil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, though this action is plain enough in it self, yet the Ceremonies that go before it, and which follow after it, are in great number, all tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to piety, and to the raising up of our affections towards Heavenly things. The Church hath prescribed them at
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:63525:51"/> the Celebration of the Divine Office of the <hi>Mass;</hi> first, to serve as exteriour marks of the Religion we profess. Next, to accommodate her self to Mans weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, who can hardly be brought to the knowledg of internal and spiritual things, but by the help of external and sensible objects. Lastly, to stir up the Devotion of the people, who behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our Ceremonies as in a picture, the greatest mysteries of our Religion represented to them, take thence oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to produce more perfect acts of Religion, as the Fathers of the Sacred <hi>Councel of Trent</hi> affirm; Ritibus ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum divinarum quae in eo Sacrifitio oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultae sunt, contemplationem, Fideles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citantur. Catech. part. 2. de Sacrific. num. 81.</p>
               <p>Nothing can be more useful to us in our Heavenly course, than to explain the chief Ceremonies the Church pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth to us in the <hi>Mass.</hi> For as they that consider with attention the works of Nature, observe that in the least crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are contained many secret won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, able to raise up the mind to the consideration of Gods power: So we may say with much more reason, that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:63525:51"/> in the spiritual world, which is the <hi>Church,</hi> the least things are full of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and deserve a pious application of mind unto them. Thus did Saint <hi>Paulin,</hi> an illustrious <hi>Roman Senator,</hi> think himself happy in having the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be employ'd in decking and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orning the Temples of God. And did not our St. <hi>Thomas of Canterbury</hi> dye, for maintaining only certain Priviledges of the Church? Nay, how many have suffered Martyrdom, for asserting the lawfulness of <hi>Pictures</hi> in our Churches, which are in the last rank of holy things. If then such small things become great in the Church, what shall we say of the <hi>Mass,</hi> which is the most Sacred thing in the whole Church? This stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Mystery heightning the worth of all that belongs to it.</p>
               <p>Now, the <hi>Jewish</hi> Ceremonies and ours, as St. <hi>Austin</hi> well observes, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in this point, that God dealt with them like gross slaves. For as a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster makes his Servant do what he pleases, without giving him accompt wherefore he commands it: so likewise God made them observe these Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Mysterious signs, without
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:63525:52"/> ever acquainting them with what they meant: Whereas <hi>Christ</hi> dealing with <hi>Christians,</hi> as a Father with his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or a Friend with a Friend, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closeth to them the secret of these Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred signs, and lets them understand what they do: <hi>I will call you no more my Servants, but my Friends; because the Servant knows not the designs of his Master, John</hi> 15. 15.</p>
               <p>So that if we compare the shaddows of the truths, we may with St. <hi>Denis</hi> distinguish three different states. That of <hi>Judaisme:</hi> That of the <hi>Church;</hi> and that of <hi>Heaven.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> had only Veils, Figures, and shaddows of the truth, which <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls, <hi>Oblatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num negotiosas scrupulositates, Lib. 2. contr. Mar. c.</hi> 8. In the <hi>Church</hi> there are shaddows, and Ceremonies still; but such are understood by us; which advantage they wanted. But in <hi>Heaven</hi> all signs and types will vanish, for we shall be fed with real truths. We ought not therefore, like <hi>Jews,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider our Ceremonies as meer orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but as objects which by their visible and dumb language, unveil many spiritual truths to the Faithfull.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:63525:52"/>
               <p>As touching the Colours of our Church Ornaments', they were chalk'd out to us by the four coulours of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>'s Vestment, mentioned <hi>Exod. 28. Religio divina alterum habet in Ministro Altaris, alterum in usu vitaque commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> saith Saint <hi>Jerome,</hi> upon the 44. Chapter of <hi>Ezechiel.</hi> Nay, in the very Law of Nature, the elder Brothers, who by their birth were <hi>Priests,</hi> had Vestures designed for that Function: Such probably was the Coat which <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca</hi> put upon <hi>Jacob,</hi> when he stole his Fathers Blessing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:63525:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. Of the general dispositions of the Assistants, for offering up the Sacrifice of the <hi>Mass.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAVING already acquainted you with outward Ceremonies, used in offering this Sacrifice of the Law of Grace; it remains to consider the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward dispositions, which are to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company our outward behaviour.</p>
               <p>As then there were three sorts of persons that assisted at the Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross; viz.</hi> the Just, the Penitent, and wicked sinners. So likewise are there three sorts of <hi>Christians,</hi> that dayly assist at the Sacrifice of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</hi> And as of those that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent at the Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross,</hi> two sorts only assisted with fruit and benefit; in like manner, two only sorts of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians</hi> reap a benefit, in assisting at the most holy Sacrifice of the <hi>Mass.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, that the Just may worthily assist thereat, they ought to come with
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:63525:53"/> such dispositions of mind, as were those of our <hi>Blessed Lady,</hi> of St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelist,</hi> of St. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and others, that assisted at the <hi>Cross,</hi> while our Saviour hung nailed, and died up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. We must therefore imitate those holy persons that stood at the foot of the <hi>Cross;</hi> those good Soules, and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the <hi>Blessed Virgin,</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed in the Mystery and necessity of our Redemption by the Passion and Death of <hi>Christ,</hi> adored God in this his great design of giving up his Son to death. So that by a lively Faith joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their intention with <hi>Christ</hi> himself, (yet compassionating his dreadfull suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings) they stood offering him up to God the Father, all the time that he was offering up himself in <hi>Holocaust</hi> to his Divine Majesty, for the expiation of the sins of Man.</p>
               <p>And that not only the innocent and just Souls, but even sinners also; I mean such as have a true desire to reform their lives, and return to God (and not the obdurat and wicked sinners) may partake of the Holy Sacrifice, and assist worthily at the same; they must follow the example of the good Thief,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:63525:54"/> who notwithstanding he had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all sorts of crimes, did, by a sudden change from the hand of God, and by an extraordinary mercy, feel at his death the powerfull effect of the Bloud of <hi>Christ</hi> dying upon the <hi>Cross.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This sinner gave pregnant testimonies of the profound humility of his heart, and of the modesty of a true Penitent, when he turned to our Saviour and said: <hi>Remember me, O Lord, when thou comest into thy Kingdom, Luc.</hi> 23. 42. He did not say, Lord, receive me into thy Kingdom; for being a sinner, he knew himself unworthy of so great a blessing, but only begs to be then remembred by him. As if he had said; Lord, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess of my crimes, is the cause of my demeriting to be admitted in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of they Servants, much less of thy Children.</p>
               <p>This great and examplar humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of this sinner on the Cross, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents to us the duty of all sinners when they assist at the Holy Sacrifice of the <hi>Mass.</hi> They should beg of <hi>Christ</hi> to be their Intercessour, and to obtain for them the spirit of true penance, and the gift of tears, to lament and bitterly
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:63525:54"/> bewail the crimes and disorders of their life past.</p>
               <p>And when they come into the <hi>Chappel,</hi> they ought to look upon the Altar as a Tribunal, whereon <hi>Christ</hi> sits in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a Judge, and from thence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces Sentences of Mercy and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, as he did upon the <hi>Cross,</hi> when he absolved the penitent Thief, and condemned the obdurate <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third sort of persons that assisted at the Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross,</hi> were very numerous, and stood scoffing at, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulting over the Son of God, whilst the far smaller number was touched with a compassion of his sufferings. The very same happens at the Sacrifice of the <hi>Altar;</hi> where this third sort I speak of, blasphem him not with their tongues, saith St. <hi>Austin,</hi> but by the disorders of their evill lives.</p>
               <p>Of this number are those that go to <hi>Mass</hi> chiefly to see and to be seen. Who go in pompous apparell, full of pride and vanity. Who go purposely to late <hi>Masses,</hi> where instead of being attentive to the Divine Mysteries, they stand gazing about, and entertain themselves with vain discourses, smiling one upon
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:63525:55"/> another, and seeking to divert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; and that in the very place where they should rather beg for tears to wash away their sins. Nay, they are so far from reflecting upon the Mystical death of <hi>Christ,</hi> that is exhibited upon the <hi>Altar</hi> for their sins, that their irreligious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, during the Sacrifice of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation and Peace, speaks them as it were resolved to provoke God to punish them. But, O most mercifull Lord, <hi>Animae irreverenti &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frunitae ne tradas eos.</hi> Eccles. 23. 6.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:63525:55"/>
            <head>✚ THE MASS EXPOUNDED in Particulars.</head>
            <head>THE FIRST PART, which is the PREPARATION OF THE OFFERERS, <hi>Answering to the first condition required for a Sacrifice, both in the Law of Nature and of</hi> Moses, <hi>namely</hi> THE SANCTIFICATION Of the Persons.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the Preparation of the Offerers, in general.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ASS is the most powerful means that is in God's Church, to force, as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> speaks, the Divine Majesty not to deny us whatever we demand of him. And because the <hi>Mass</hi> is the prime
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:63525:56"/> and most effectual of all Prayers, it is therefore stiled by the Holy Fathers, <hi>The Prayer of Oblation,</hi> in which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Principle, the Chief Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Mediator of all Grace; who also grants it as a <hi>Lord,</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster like, sets it a work in the Body of his Church.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Mass, Christ</hi> sacrifizeth himself for each of us, as often as we will, and that is it, that makes the Prayers we offer to God at <hi>Mass</hi> so effectual, that by the Oblation thereof, it is almost impossible we should be deny'd what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we demand either of him, or of his Father by him. Nay, one only of these Oblations would be sufficient, if we went prepared to it as we ought.</p>
               <p>This makes me fear, both for my self and for all those that assist at <hi>Mass;</hi> because methinks one should come with more reverence, and with greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion then usually we do: for extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Mysteries require extraordinary Preparations. Nor must they other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise be approached unto, than with that reverence which is due to sacred things. And we do but expose our selves to the indignation of Heaven,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:63525:56"/> when we think to partake of them, without that preparation, which their stupendious holiness requires.</p>
               <p>That we may therefore hear <hi>Mass</hi> with those dispositions which each qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity it is attended with, exacts; we must know that as there are three sorts of Sacrifices, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> of <hi>Moses,</hi> and of <hi>Grace,</hi> there are likewise three sorts of Preparations, formerly termed the <hi>Sanctification of the Persons,</hi> that were to offer and assist at the Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>The Sanctification, in the Law of Nature, we find mentioned in <hi>Job</hi> 1. 4. where it is said, that <hi>He sanctified his Children,</hi> before he offered up Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices for them. But what Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies they made use of at this first sort of Sanctification, we find not recorded. Yet we may well suppose it to have been some Religious act, which right Reason suggested to them.</p>
               <p>The second sort of Sanctification or Preparation of the Persons before the Sacrfice, we find in the first Book of <hi>Kings,</hi> where the Prophete <hi>Samuel</hi> said to the Masters of Families; <hi>I come to offer Sacrifices to the Lord, sanctify your selves, and come with me, that I may
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:63525:57"/> offer.</hi> Isay <hi>then sanctified his Children, and called them to the Sacrifice; Chap.</hi> 16. 5. And this was a Legal Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which consisted for the most part in outward Ceremonies, as wash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Cloaths and their Bodies; <hi>Levit, 22. 6. Exod.</hi> 19. 10. In abstaining from Women, <hi>&amp;c. 1. Reg.</hi> 21. 4. and from touching unclean things, as dead Bodies, worms, or such insects; <hi>Levit.</hi> 22. 4, 5. In abstaining from Wine, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10. 8. And in the going bare-foot to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar; <hi>Exod.</hi> 30. 9.</p>
               <p>The third sort of Sanctification, is that of the <hi>Christian</hi> Offerers in the Law of Grace, which for the most part is all interiour; though some times ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with watching and fasting.</p>
               <p>And this Interiour Sanctification, consists, in sequestring our thoughts from wordly cares and businesses. In considering with an humble and peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent heart, the Religious Work we are about: <hi>I have given you an example</hi> of humility, <hi>that you do even as I have done; John</hi> 13. 15. And in sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Soules, with the word of God, &amp; his divine Truths: <hi>Sanctify them in thy Truth: thy word is truth it self, John</hi> 17. 17.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:63525:57"/> For our Mysteries receive strength and vigour from the Sacred Writings.</p>
               <p>And indeed the reading of Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, is an excellent Preparation to this great Action, and to the eating of the Heavenly Bread. This, <hi>Christ</hi> teaches us in the <hi>Gospel,</hi> when intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to give, for the first time, his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal and glorify'd Body to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciples, he prepared them thereto, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the fire of his Love in their hearts by his words: <hi>Did not our bearts,</hi> said they, <hi>burn within us, while he talked with us by the way, Luke</hi> 23. 32. And where it is said in the <hi>Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi> that the Primitive <hi>Christians</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued <hi>In the breaking of Bread;</hi> that is to say, in the Communion of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice: it is also said, that they <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the doctrine of the Apostles; Acts</hi> 2. 42.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:63525:58"/>
               <head>INTROIBO AD ALTARE, &amp;c. <hi>page 2. OR THE PUBLICK APOLOGY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Priest being vested, comes to the lower step of the Altar, where both he and the People, considering their own unworthiness to assist at such sacred Mysteries, as knowing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves guilty of humane frailties, or hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and secret sins, they begin to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore his mercy, in rehearsing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther several Prayers, which were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently stiled <hi>Apologies.</hi> They were so called, because the Priest and the People do thereby excuse themselves, and make their Apology, for presuming to offer up this Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>Several kind of these Apologies are to he seen in the ancient <hi>Liturgies</hi> col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by <hi>Menardus.</hi> They consisted chiefly in two thing; in Psalms, and a publick Confession: and though these two parts varied in most Churches, yet
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:63525:58"/> all of them aimed at the same end: That is, to acknowledge their own unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiness.</p>
               <p>This first Ceremony of the Priest's standing off from the Altar, with the humble <hi>Publican;</hi> is to teach us, to make our approaches to God, and to his Holy Altar, in a way worthy of himself; and that we may understand the great danger we incur by displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing so dreadful a <hi>Majesty,</hi> to whom, <hi>Abraham,</hi> looking upon himself as dust and ashes, durst hardly presume to speak; <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 27.</p>
               <p>The Priest then reflecting within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, that the Altar represents to us <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> glorified; awakes as it were his Faith, and by an awful fear makes him look upon the Altar, as <hi>Moses</hi> and the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> did upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> in thunder and lightning, of which the Scripture sayes; <hi>The whole Mountain was terrible: Exod.</hi> 19. 18.</p>
               <p>Now, seing the Altar represents to us <hi>Christ</hi> glorified, as after his Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, we must look upon it as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presenting him such, and according to the draught he hath given us of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:63525:59"/> in that condition, and as he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to his beloved St. <hi>John Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelist,</hi> in the Isle of <hi>Patmos:</hi> where on a sudden, he heard a voice that bid him write what he saw. And at the same time he perceived seven golden candlesticks, and in the midst of them a Man full of Majesty, and clad in a Priestly Vestment, girt with a golden girdle. His hair was white as snow, his eyes sparkling as fire, his face shin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like the <hi>Sun</hi> at noon: He had a sword in his mouth; he held in his hands seven stars; and when he spake, his voice was like the noise of a great multitude of waters. And doubtless this Man was <hi>Christ-</hi>risen and glorious, as all the circumstances evince it.</p>
               <p>This certainly is a Divine Figure, and worthy of God made Man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come immortal and glorious. None but God could have so depainted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to us. We could, 'tis true, have represented to our selves <hi>Christ</hi> born in a Manger, his leading a poor life, and dying naked upon a Cross, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in these particulars, he acted as Man: But as he is now risen full of glory, even in his humanity, we could
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:63525:59"/> not frame in our minds any shape that could truly represent him. This Figure is admirable, in that it is the picture of <hi>Christ,</hi> drawn by himself, which renders visible and sensible to us, his invisible and spiritual manner of residing on the <hi>Altar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us therefore reflect on the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the <hi>Church,</hi> in ordering this Ceremony, of the Priest's beginning <hi>Mass</hi> at a distance from the <hi>Altar,</hi> thereby to strike in us an awful respect thereof. Here before any nearer approach, he repeats the Psalm <hi>Judica me, Deus,</hi> by which he begs to be deliver'd, by the assistance of God's comfortable light, from his fears of God's wrath, and that he may be admitted to the <hi>Altar.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Confiteor Deo, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p>HAving ended the Psalm <hi>Judica me Deus,</hi> here the Priest begins to make the Publick Confession, saying the <hi>Confiteor.</hi> For the Priest reflecting, that St. <hi>John</hi> was commanded to bid the Angel, that is the <hi>Bishop of Ephesus,</hi> to do penance; though but a moment before, <hi>Christ</hi> himself had commended
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:63525:60"/> his good life, his labours, and his zeal against the wicked; hath good reason to think that he hears a voice coming forth from the <hi>Altar,</hi> commanding him to purify his Conscience, and to have a care how he approach the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> of the <hi>Lord: Sacerdates qui accedunt ad Dominum, sanctificentur, ne percutiat eos, Exod.</hi> 19. 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Deus tu conversus, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p>THe Priest and the People, having publickly confessed their sins, and their unworthiness, they are encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by comfortable passages of Scripture: whereupon the Priest, presuming on God's mercy and goodness, ventures with an humble confidence, to go to the <hi>Altar,</hi> which he kisseth in token of the Love and Union of the <hi>Church,</hi> to <hi>Christ</hi> our <hi>Saviour: Accede ad me, &amp; da mihi osculum, fili mi; Genes.</hi> 27. 26.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:63525:60"/>
               <head>INTROITƲS. <hi>pag.</hi> 10.</head>
               <p>NOW, the Priest being up at the <hi>Altar,</hi> goes to the left side thereof, where blessing himself with the sign of the <hi>Cross,</hi> he sayes the <hi>Anthem</hi> called the <hi>Introit,</hi> which signifies <hi>Entrance;</hi> that is to say, that here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly begins the <hi>Mass.</hi> For this <hi>Introit,</hi> or <hi>Ingressa,</hi> as the <hi>Ambrosians</hi> call it, alwayes contains in brief, the subject of the <hi>Mass;</hi> that is, the peculiar so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of the Day, whether a Sunday or Holy day: only with this difference, that sometimes it contains it, literally and clcarly, and at other times mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and obscurely.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Introit</hi> is to the rest of the <hi>Mass</hi> for that day, as the Text is to the rest of the Sermon, containing it all in few words. It is in respect to the Office of the <hi>Mass,</hi> as the <hi>Invitatorium</hi> is to the Office of the <hi>Breviary.</hi> Let us take for instance the <hi>Invitatory</hi> of the Blessed <hi>Trinity; Deum verum unum in Trinitate, &amp; Trinitatem in unitate, venite adoremus.</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:63525:61"/> Now, be pleased but to consider this <hi>Introit</hi> of the <hi>Mass</hi> of the Blessed <hi>Trinity, Benedicta sit, &amp;c.</hi> pag. 6. and confer it with the Prayer, Epistle, Gospel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and you will find they are but exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and enlargements of the <hi>Introit;</hi> which therefore is always twice, and in some Churches thrice repeated, that it may enter deeper into our minds.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Kyrie eleison, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 10.</head>
                  <p>HAving heard and ponder'd the great Mysteries proposed to us in the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troit,</hi> and understanding at the same time what duties are required from us to enter into the spirit of these Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or to follow the example and vertues of <hi>Christ,</hi> or his Saints; and finding in our selves a great weakness in order to their performance, we here call upon the powerful assistance of God's grace, and implore his Divine mercy in these short and moving expressions: <hi>Kyrie eleison. Lord have mercy upon us. Christ have mercy upon us, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Gloria in excelsis, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 12.</head>
                  <p>HEre the Faithful praise God, for the Mystery or divine Truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:63525:61"/> to us in the <hi>Introit.</hi> And this by the Canticle which the Angels were heard to sing at the Birth and first dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of <hi>Christ</hi> made to the World.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Dominus vobiscum, <hi>p.</hi> 12.</head>
                  <p>AFter the <hi>Kyrie eleison,</hi> or the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Hymne, the Priest turns towards the People, and salutes them, saying, <hi>Dominus vobiscum;</hi> That is, <hi>Our Lord be with you.</hi> By which words of the Priest, <hi>Christ</hi> is undestood to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute us by him, as desiring to be with us till the end of the World, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 21. thereby to unite us to himself, and make us his living Temples, in receiving the blessed <hi>Eucharist,</hi> as the Angel said to the ever blessed <hi>Virgin Mary, Dominus tecum,</hi> before <hi>Christ</hi> took Flesh in her Womb, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 28.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Dominus vobiscum,</hi> is a token of peace and Communion, and so therefore often repeated; and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly after the <hi>Kyrie eleison,</hi> or <hi>Gloria in excelsis,</hi> to dispose the People to pray for a further enlightning of us in the Mystery, briefly touched in the <hi>Introit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:63525:62"/>
                  <head>Oratio seu Collecta, <hi>p.</hi> 12.</head>
                  <p>NOw, the Priest comes to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayer, stiled by the <hi>Church the Collect.</hi> But before he begins, he excites both himself and the People thereto, saying; <hi>Oremus Let us pray:</hi> at which warning, it was the custom for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly by all that were present, to fall to their prayers in silence; and after a little while, the Priest collecting, as it were, all the vows and prayers of the People into a short one, said it afterwards in a loud voice, as an Embassador sent from the People to God the Father, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent him their addresses.</p>
                  <p>On fasting dayes, the Priest used to bid them kneel down at their prayers, saying; <hi>Flectamus genua.</hi> And after a little while the <hi>Deacon</hi> bade them rise, saying; <hi>Levate:</hi> After which the Priest said the <hi>Collect,</hi> to the end that by the multitude of their prayers in one, they might be rendred more effectual to move God to grant their Petitious: And at last he concluded as we now do this publick Prayer or Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, in the name of <hi>Christ</hi> our Mediator,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:63525:62"/> as he himself bids us, saying; <hi>Whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye demand of my Father in my name, he will grant it to you, John</hi> 16. 22.</p>
                  <p>While the Priest is saying the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayer at the Altar, we should joyn our intention with his, or frame in our minds some short Prayer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the subject of the day: And for such as cannot make any of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, I have here added half a douzen of the chiefest Prayers of the <hi>Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer to beg Humility:</head>
                  <head type="sub">Deus, qui superbis, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>O God, the, Resister of the proud, and forgiver of the humble, grant us the vertue of true humility, whereof thy Son hath given a pattern to all <hi>Christians,</hi> in his own Sacred Person; and that we may never draw upon us thy wrath by our pride, but rather receive the gifts of thy grace by our submissiveness: Through <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:63525:63"/>
                  <head>For the Remission of sins.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Deus, qui nullum, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>O God, who rejectest none, but doest mercifully receive even the greatest sinners, when they do penance for their crimes; consider, we beseech thee, our humble addresses, enlighten our hearts, and enable us to fullfil thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Through <hi>Christ, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>To lead a life worthy of the quality of a <hi>Christian.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">Deus, qui errantibus, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>O God, who disclosest the light of thy Truth even to them that run astray, to the end they may return to the way of Justice; grant, we beseech thee, to all that bear the Title of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> Grace to detest whatever is contrary to so Holy a Name, and to take upon them what so Divine a call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing requires from them: Through <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:63525:63"/>
                  <head>To beg the fear and love of God.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Sancti Nominis tui, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>LOrd grant us continually an awful and ardent love of thy holy Name; since thou doest never abandon those whom thou hast established in the soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of thy love: Through <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>To implore the increase of Faith, Hope, and Charity.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Omnipotens sempiterne Deus, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>ETernal and Almighty God, grant us still to increase in Faith, Hope and Charity: and to the end we may obtain what thou hast promised to us, make us alwayes love what thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandest: Through <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>To beg for patience in our sufferings.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Deus qui nos, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>O God, who knowest us to be set in so great dangers, that we cannot
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:63525:64"/> (through humane frailty) subsist; grant us health of mind and body, that by thy assistance we may overcome what we suffer for our sins: Through <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="reading">
                  <head>Lectio Epistolae, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 14.</head>
                  <p>AFter the <hi>Collect,</hi> is read a Lesson out of Holy Scripture, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times out of the Old Testament; but for the most part out of the New, and especially out of the Epistles of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> from whence this Lesson takes the name of <hi>Epistle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Lesson, called the <hi>Epistle,</hi> is an Exposition at length of the Mystery, mentioned in the <hi>Introit;</hi> This Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition is not alwayes literal, but often allegorical, mystical, or tropological: As for instance, this Epistle or Lesson of the Blessed <hi>Trinity,</hi> beginning; <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dete, perfecti estote, &amp;c.</hi> mystically in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structs us that the <hi>Trinity</hi> consists in three Divine Persons here mentioned, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghost.</p>
                  <p>This reading of the Holy Scriptures at the Celebration of the Sacrifice of the <hi>Evangelical Law,</hi> is derived from
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:63525:64"/> the <hi>Old;</hi> where in <hi>Exodus</hi> 24. 7. we find that <hi>Moses</hi> took the Volume of the Law, and read it before the Altar, where they offered <hi>Holocaust</hi> and <hi>Peace-Offerings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They that have the <hi>Catholick</hi> Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, do well to read over the <hi>Epistle</hi> and <hi>Gospel</hi> of the day, before they go to <hi>Mass,</hi> and to reflect upon them while the Priest reads the <hi>Epistle</hi> at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. But for such as have it not, let them be pleased to read over one or two of these following <hi>Maxims,</hi> and meditate upon them while the <hi>Epistle</hi> is read or sung.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apostolical_maxims">
               <head>APOSTOLICAL MAXIMS.</head>
               <p n="1">1. TO be true <hi>Christians,</hi> according to these sacred words, we must renounce our selves, and live no longer for our selves, but for God. <hi>You are not your own, for you are purchased at a dear rate, 1 Cor.</hi> 6. 20.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:63525:65"/>II. A <hi>Christian</hi> ought to be free from self-interest, solicitude and avarice. <hi>Let your life be free from all coveteousness. Be contented with what you have, since God himself hath said: I will not leave you, nor forsake you, Hebr.</hi> 13. 5.</p>
               <p n="3">III. We deceive our selves in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, that we love God and our Neighbour, if we show it not by our works. <hi>If any one having the goods of this World, and sees his brother in want, and is not moved so far as to assist him, how can be believe that he loves God? 1 John</hi> 3. 17.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. That we are not only obliged to do good works, but we must per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them for the love of God, and with intention to please him; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise 'tis not sufficient, <hi>Whether you eat, whether you drink, or whatever you do, do it for the Glory of God, 1 Cor.</hi> 11. 31.</p>
               <p n="5">V. That every <hi>Christian</hi> is bound to take <hi>Christ</hi> for the patern of his life. <hi>Be you followers of God as his dear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and practise love and charity, after the example of</hi> Christ, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5. 1.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. That according to the word of God, we are not in the state of a true <hi>Christian,</hi> unless we lead a life free from
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:63525:65"/> mortal sin. <hi>How can we, that are dead to sin, think to live in it, knowing that our Old man is crucified with</hi> Christ, <hi>that the Body of sin might be destroyed, and that henceforth we should serve sin no more, Rom. 6. 2, &amp;</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Reciprocal duties of Married People. <hi>Women, be submissive to your Husbands, in consideration of the Lord, as your duty binds you; Colloss. 3. 18. Now, Husbands love your Wives, as</hi> Christ <hi>loves his Church; Ephes.</hi> 5. 12. That is with a holy, faithful, indissolvable, and tender Love.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Of the modesty which <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian</hi> Women ought to observe in their attire. <hi>The Women, that they attire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves modestly, and that the manner of their apparel have nothing hut what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces to honesty and chastity; let them not curl their hair, nor adorn themselves with gold, nor pearl, nor costly apparel; 1 Tim. 2. 9. But let their ornament be that of their Soul, which consists in an inward and invisible Beauty hidden in the heart, and in the purity of a meek and quiet spirit, which is a rich and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ornament in the sight of God, 1 Peter</hi> 3. 4.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:63525:66"/>IX. Of bearing one with anothers imperfections. <hi>Bear you one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, so shall you fullfil the Law of</hi> Christ; <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 2. A very important Maxim for those that live together in Families.</p>
               <p n="10">X. A <hi>Christian</hi> Man ought alwayes so to live contented in his Calling. <hi>Let every man abide in the same condition wherein he is called; 1 Cor.</hi> 7. 20.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. We must withdraw our affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the love of the World, and from all Creatures. <hi>Love not the World, nor the things that are in the World; 1 John</hi> 2. 15.</p>
               <p n="12"> XII. We ought to be carefull of trifling away our time in idle Past-times and Recreations. <hi>Brethren, redeem time; Coloss.</hi> 4. 5. that is far from giving leave to spend it idly as many do at Cards, and other Games.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Graduale, <hi>p.</hi> 14.</head>
                  <p>AS after all the Lessons read in the Church, there is alwayes said a Responsatory; so likewise to this Lesson of the <hi>Epistle</hi> is there added a Respon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satory, called the <hi>Gradual;</hi> because it was sung while the <hi>Deacon</hi> came so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:63525:66"/> attended from the Altar, and went up the steps of a High Pulpit, (the word <hi>Gradual,</hi> signifies a <hi>step</hi> or <hi>degree)</hi> there to read the Gospel, the better to be heard throughout the Church: <hi>Preach you on the top of Houses, what hath been said to you in your ear; Matth.</hi> 10. 27.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Gradual Responsory,</hi> is alwayes some pithy Versicle of a <hi>Psalm</hi> in praise and thanksgiving to God for the Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, imparted to us in the Lesson of the <hi>Mass.</hi> This we may see in the <hi>Gradual</hi> of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> where <hi>Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus es Domine, &amp;c.</hi> is thrice repeated, we thereby blessing the Soveraign and independent. Being of the three Divine Persons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Sequentia sancti Evang. &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 16.</head>
                  <p>HEre is read the Gospel, which is the most excellent Preparation for disposing our selves to the offering of this Great Sacrifice of the New Law. For it is not only a fuller and more lively Exposition of what was glanced at in the <hi>Introit;</hi> but it contains for the most part some exemplar passage of our Saviours own actions. The Gospel,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:63525:67"/> say the Holy <hi>Fathers,</hi> is the mouth of <hi>Christ,</hi> by which though sitting in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, he speaks continually on Earth. The precepts of the Gospel, saith St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> are the food of our hearts: In this Book we find a light to lead us, strength to uphold us, and remedies to cure us.</p>
                  <p>And because the Translation of all the Gospels throughout the whole Year, would have made this Book of a great bulk, I have only inserted some few of its choisest Maxims, which the <hi>Reader</hi> may reflect upon, while the Gospel is reading. These Maxims are as many Lessons given us by <hi>Christ,</hi> whom the Eternal Father bids us harken to, as to our only Master and true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. But upon the Solemn dayes of the Mysteries of <hi>Christ</hi>'s Life, such as <hi>Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Easter, &amp;c.</hi> I would advice the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> to call to mind the History thereof, as also to make some reflection on the Life of the <hi>Saint,</hi> whose Feast is cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="evangelical_maxims">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:63525:67"/>
               <head>EVANGELICAL MAXIMS:</head>
               <p n="1">I. THat to be saved, we must love God with all our heart, and our Neighbour as our selves. <hi>Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy Soul, with all thy force, and with all thy mind: and thy Neighbour as thy self: Do so, and thou shalt obtain everlasting life; Luke.</hi> 10. 25.</p>
               <p n="2">II. That to be saved, one must keep God's Commandments, and practise good works: <hi>If thou wilt enjoy everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, keep the Commandments; Matth.</hi> 17. 19.</p>
               <p n="3">III. That the omission of works of Charity towards our Neighbour, will cause the loss of many a Christian: <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me you accursed into everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fire, prepared for the Devil and his angels: For I was hungry, and you gave me not to eat; I was thirsty, and you gave me not to drink; Matth.</hi> 21. 41. Note, that those are not damn'd for swearing, stealing, drinking, and for
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:63525:68"/> their lusts, or for other actual evill; but meerly for not doing good.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. That according to the words of <hi>Christ,</hi> we cannot serve nor love God and the World together: <hi>None can serve two Masters; you cannot serve God and money; Matth. 6. 24. Luke</hi> 16. 13.</p>
               <p n="5">V. That the way which leads to Heaven, is narrow; and in which there are but few that walk: <hi>Enter you by the narrow gate, for wide is the way that leads to perdition: And many there are who enter by it. How straight is the gate, and narrow the way which leads to Life! and how few there are that find it! Matth. 7. 13, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. That according to the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, when a <hi>Christian</hi> hath been so unhappy as to fall into sin, there is no other way for him to be saved, but by doing true penance: <hi>If you do not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, you shall all perish, Luke</hi> 13. 5.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. How carefully we ought to avoid the giving scandal, or to be the occasion of it: <hi>It were better for a Man that be had a mill-stone about his neck, and that he were cast into the Sea, than to have been occasion of scandal to the least
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:63525:68"/> of these that believe in me, Marke 9. 14. Matth. 18. 6. Luke</hi> 17. 2.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. That we must continually imitate the mildness and humility of <hi>Christ,</hi> which are the chief vertues he would have us to learn of him: <hi>Learn of me to be humble and mild of heart, Matth.</hi> 11. 29. Yet a cross word, or even a frowning countenance, set us on fire.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. The <hi>Christians</hi> duty towards Kings and Magistrates; <hi>Let all People submit to Superior Powers: for there is no Power hut what comes from God, and it is he that hath ordained such powers on Earth; Rom.</hi> 13. 1.</p>
               <p n="10">X. The main business of a <hi>Christian</hi> in this World, is to save his Soul, and all his actions ought to aim thereat; Nothing is good, but what promotes it; and nothing bad, but what hinders it: <hi>What would it avail a Man to gain all the World, if he looseth his own Soul</hi> by sin; <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 26.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. All sollicitude, troubles, disquiet, and fear for the future, even for neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, as food, and cloathing, are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to <hi>Christians: Be not solicitous for what you shall eat, nor yet for apparel, as Heathens are: your Heavenly Father
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:63525:69"/> knows you want these things; Matth.</hi> 6. 31. Yet a diligent care is not forbid.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. We ought to judge of earthly things by the Maxims of Faith, that is as God and his Angels judge of them, and not by the false Maxims of the World: <hi>The just Man lives by Faith; Gal.</hi> 3. 11. What is a sinner, for example, in the eyes of Faith, that is of Truth? A blind Man; <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 35. A beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar; <hi>Luke</hi> 15. 14. A slave; <hi>Marke</hi> 52. A paralitick; <hi>Matth.</hi> 9. 2. Deaf, <hi>Marke</hi> 7. 32. Naked; <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 11. Dead; <hi>Luke</hi> 7. 12.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Credo in Ʋnum Deum, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 20.</head>
                  <p>NExt is said the <hi>Constantinopolitan Creed,</hi> which is an excellent Confession of Faith, and a summary of our Belief, to testify that we firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Holy Instructions, that we have received both in the <hi>Epistle</hi> and <hi>Gospel;</hi> whereof we make here a solemn and publick Profession. And thus we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this first part of the Holy Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the <hi>Mass,</hi> which is the <hi>Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:63525:69"/> of the Offerers.</hi> Let us then prepare our selves in this first part as we ought; for I much fear lest the little attention which is given by most to this Great Sacrifice, (unless it be when they are to receive) may make it wholy fruitless to them. <hi>Sanctificamini filii Israel, &amp; estote parati; Breviar. in Vig. Nat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:63525:70"/>
            <head>✚ THE SECOND PART, which is the PREPARATION OF THE BREAD AND WINE For the Sacrifice; Answering to the second condition required for a Sacrifice in the Old Law; <hi>viz.</hi> THE SANCTIFICATION Of the <hi>Victim.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of this Preparation in general.</head>
               <p>HAVING prepared the Offerers for a worthy assisting at the Sacrifice, we come now to prepare the intended <hi>Victim,</hi> and make it fit to be presented to the Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty: Where we must note by the by;
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:63525:70"/> That this Second Part is no more es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sential to the Sacrifice, than the first; both of them varying in several <hi>Churches,</hi> as being but Ceremonial Preparations to the Sacrifice. And this our Second is the first part among the <hi>Greeks,</hi> who perform it with great pomp and Ceremonies, far beyond the <hi>Latines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This part of the <hi>Mass,</hi> corresponds to the second condition required for a a Sacrifice in the <hi>Mosaical Law; viz. The Sanctification of the Victim.</hi> And this Sanctification of the victim required four conditions: The <hi>first</hi> of which was, The perfection of the Victim; which perfection excluded all blemishes: <hi>If it hath a spot, or it be lame, or blind, or deformed in any part, or weak, it shall not be offered to God; Deut.</hi> 15. 21. The <hi>second</hi> was a separation and disingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it from the dominion of Man, by which the victim being dedicated to God, could no longer be imployed in any profane use; <hi>Exod.</hi> 35. 5. The <hi>third</hi> was a supernatural Sanctification, which elevated the Victim above its own nature, and stampt it with a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Character. The <hi>fourth</hi> was an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to die, and to be destroy'd;
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:63525:71"/> this last being essential to a Sacrifice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Offertorium, <hi>p.</hi> 20.</head>
               <p>AFter the <hi>Creed</hi> and the <hi>Gospel,</hi> the Priest sayes the <hi>Anthem,</hi> called the <hi>Offertory:</hi> because antiently it was sung, while the People brought and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to God Bread and Wine for the Sacrifice, or Money for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Ministers of the Altar, saying: <hi>Tua de tuis offerimus tibi, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This our <hi>Offertory</hi> in the New Law, answers to the Perfection of the Victim, required in the Old. For it is of the best wheaten Bread, without leven; leven being a symbol of corruption and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection. <hi>Purge out therefore the old leven,</hi> saith the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 7. The form or figure is a Circle, that being accompted the most perfect of all fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="practical_directions">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:63525:71"/>
               <head>PRACTICAL Directions.</head>
               <p>WHile the <hi>Offertory</hi> and the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Oblations are made by the Priest, let us reflect on some of the most Illustrious offerers: for instance, on the Blessed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> buying a pair of Turtle-Doves at the Temple gate, and offering them up to the Eternal Father. Let us further consider and joyn our affections with the Kings that came from the <hi>East,</hi> to make their Offerings of <hi>Gold, Myrrhe,</hi> and <hi>Frank-intense,</hi> to Blessed JESUS. And after their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, let us dedicate and consecrate to God, Our Estate, our Fortune; our good Name, our dearest Friends, and all whatsoever is ours: They are all his, and we have only the use of them by his Grant.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Suscipe, sancte Pater, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 20.</head>
                  <p>THe Priest having taken possession of the Gifts and Offerings, he now presents them to God the Father,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:63525:72"/> holding up the <hi>Host</hi> upon the silver Patene, according to God's express command in <hi>Exodus</hi> 29. 22. saying: <hi>Thou shalt sanctify them, holding them up before the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this Oblation the Bread is dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to God; and so becomes disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged from the Dominion of Man, and is no longer suffered to be imploy'd in any profane use. The like is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood of the Wine. And this Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony answers to the second Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion required in the Old Law, for the Sanctification of the <hi>Victim.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To avoid confusion, note; That this Oblation here made, is only a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Oblation of the <hi>Gifts,</hi> that is, of the Bread and Wine designed for the future Sacrifice; and not the great Oblation essential to a sacrifice, which is made of the precious <hi>Body and Bloud of Christ,</hi> immediately after the Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Deus qui humanae, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 22.</head>
                  <p>THe Priest havig put the Wine into the Chalice; saying this Prayer, he mingles a little Water with the said
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:63525:72"/> Wine. And this mixture is termed by the <hi>Church, A Great Mystery,</hi> as these words of the Prayer import: <hi>Per hujus aquae &amp; vini Mysterium;</hi> and that with very good reason. For this mixture of Wine and Water, is an express symbol of the fruit principally intended in this Sacrifice, which is the union and partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation which <hi>Christians</hi> ought to share at the Altar with <hi>Christ,</hi> if they expect to be made partakers of his Glory in Heaven; as these same following words of the same Prayer intimate to us: <hi>Da nobis per hujus aquae &amp; vini mysterium, ejus Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis esse consortes.</hi> For the Wine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presents <hi>Christ,</hi> and the Water the People. Nor is this comparing the People to Water, a groundless similitude; but warranted out of the <hi>Apocalypse,</hi> where the Angel said to St. <hi>John: These wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which thou hast seen, are People and Nations, Apoc. 17. 15, &amp; 1.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> hath a long Letter to <hi>Caecilianus,</hi> concerning this Ceremony. <hi>The Water</hi> (saith he) <hi>signifies to us the People, and the Wine our Saviour</hi> Christ: <hi>And when water is mingled with wine in the Chalice, it is to show that the Faithful are united with</hi> Christ, <hi>in whom
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:63525:73"/> they believe. And as the wine and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are so united and mingled together in the Chalice, that they become inseparable; so nothing can separate the Faithful, that is the</hi> Church, <hi>from our Saviour</hi> Christ.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Priest therefore ought not to consecrate water alone, nor wine alone: For should be consecrate wine alone, the Bloud of</hi> Christ <hi>would be without us; and if the water were alone, then should we be without</hi> Christ. <hi>NAM si vinum solum quis offerat, sanguis Christi incipit esse sine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis: Si vero aqua sit sola, plebs incipit esse sine Christe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>These weighty words of Saint <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> sufficiently inform us, That by this Ceremeny of mingling water with the wine, a Great Mystery is intimated to us. For in this Action, <hi>Christ</hi> unites himself with all the <hi>Church</hi> in two wayes, which may seem perhaps incredible to those that are little acquainted with the Mysteries of our Religion. For in the <hi>Mass</hi> he offers his natural Body for the whole Church; and together with his natural Body, he offers the whole Church, which is his Mystical Body.</p>
                  <p>This Doctrine is asserted by that most Eminent Doctor of the Church Saint
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:63525:73"/>
                     <hi>Austin,</hi> whose words are too express to be omitted: <hi>Per hoc</hi> Christus <hi>Sacerdos est, ipse offerens, ipse &amp; oblatio, cujus rei Sacramentum quotidianum esse voluit Eeclesiae Sacrificium; quae cum ejus capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis corpus sit, seipsam per ipsum, discit offerre. St. Aug. de Civit. Dei lib. 10. cap.</hi> 20. And in the same Book he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats it again, in these terms: <hi>In Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento Altaris Fidelibus noto frequentat Ecclesia, ubi eidem demonstratur, quod in ea Oblatione quam offert, ipsa offera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Ibid cap.</hi> 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Offerimus tibi, Domine, Calicem, &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 22.</head>
                  <p>THe Priest having offered the Bread in his own name, saying; <hi>Suseipe—Hostiam quam ego famulus tuus offerro, &amp;c.</hi> now he makes the Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Wine and Water in the name of all the Assistants, saying: <hi>Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus tibi, Domine, Calicem, &amp;c.</hi> To signify, that in the water the People offer up themselves with <hi>Christ,</hi> as we have said above. And upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt it is, that at <hi>High Mass,</hi> the <hi>Deacon</hi> representing the People, holds
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:63525:74"/> up the Chalice with the Priest, and at the same time, pronounces the words <hi>Offerimus, &amp;c.</hi> which the <hi>Deacon</hi> doth not at the Oblation of the <hi>Host.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And for asmuch as it is of great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that this important truth be well understood, let us consult St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and he will tell us how and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we shall make this Offering, to the end it may be acceptable to God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beseech you,</hi> (saith he to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans) that you give up your bodies a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Sacrifice, holy and agreable to God, Rom.</hi> 12. 1. He calls it a Living Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, to distinguish it from the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the Old Law, which were dead beasts: And also that we might not think, that he commands us to give up our Bodies in a bloudy way.</p>
                  <p>The Apostle likewise will have this Sacrifice of our Bodies to be <hi>Holy,</hi> that is to be free from all spot of sin, and chiefly of impurity; <hi>For this,</hi> continues he, <hi>is the will of God, that you be holy, and that you abstain from fornication.</hi> And to offer up our Bodies by a continued chain of good works, to God's honour and glory.</p>
                  <p>After the Sacrifice of the Body, the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:63525:74"/> Apostle exhorts us to the Sacrifice of our Mind, in the following words: <hi>Be you changed by the renewing of your mind.</hi> And Saint <hi>Austin</hi> teaches admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable well, how this renewing of mind is done: Our Soul (saith he) enflamed with the love of God, loses the shape that worldly affections had imprinted on it, and is changed and transformed as it were into God: <hi>Anima nostra fit Sacrificium cum se refert ad Deum, ut igne amoris accensa, eique tanquam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutabili formae subdita, reformetur. In Epist. Joan. Tract.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>The third thing we are to offer to God, is our heart, as the same St. <hi>Paul</hi> continues to exhort us, saying: <hi>That you may know what is the will of God.</hi> By these words, teaching us to sacrifice our will to God, in subduing it to his; for an humble and penitent heart is an excellent Sacrifice in Saint <hi>Austin</hi>'s Judgment: <hi>Humilitas cordis sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium est; in Psal.</hi> 130. And indeed the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> assures us by the mouth of <hi>David,</hi> That an afflicted spirit, is the Sacrifice that God demands; <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium Deo spiritus contribulatus. Ps.</hi> 50.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:63525:75"/>
                  <head>Veni Sanctificator, &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 22.</head>
                  <p>THe Priest having dedicated both the Bread and the Wine, he now bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses them with the sign of the Cross, and calls upon the Holy Ghost, That he would vouchsafe to come and give a supernatural Sanctification to the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations or Gifts designed for the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: And this in the whole <hi>Mass,</hi> is the only Prayer directed to the Holy Ghost.</p>
                  <p>This Ceremony answers to the third and fourth conditions required to the <hi>Victim</hi> in the Old Law. For the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of the Holy Ghost upon the Oblation, raiseth it above its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by a supernatural Sanctification. And the obligation of destroying it to the honour of God, is denoted by the sign of the Cross made upon the Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings; the stamp of the Cross being a visible mark or sign of death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:63525:75"/>
                  <head>Lavabo inter innocentes, &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 24.</head>
                  <p>THe Oblation of the Bread and Wine being made, the Priest washes his hands, in token of the exteriour purity and cleaness, with which we ought to be present at this Sacred Mystery. This purity was figured in the Old Law, by the brazen Vessels made of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's mirrours, <hi>Exod</hi> 38. 8. in which the Priests were to wash themselves before the Sacrifices, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30. 18. For as the right use of a mirrour is to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover any spots in the face, or inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency in the dress: so in the New Law, this Ceremony signifies, that we ought to be present at the Sacrifice, with all cleaness and decency.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Suscipe Sancta Trinitas, &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 24.</head>
                  <p>HEre again the Priest makes an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Bread and Wine to the Blessed <hi>Trinity,</hi> in memory of <hi>Christ</hi>'s Sacred Humanity in the most essential Mysteries of our Salvation, and in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:63525:76"/> of the greatest Saints in Heaven; that is to give God thanks, saith St. <hi>Austin,</hi> for their great victories; and to encourage us by their Intercession, to follow their examples: <hi>Ʋt Deo de illorum victoriis gratias agamus, &amp; nos ad imitationem talium coronarum atque Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum, eodem invocato in auxilium, ex eorum memoriae renovatione adhortemur:</hi> St. <hi>Aug. de Civit. Dei lib. 8. e. ult.</hi> But for our further satisfaction, let us hear our Holy Mother the <hi>Church</hi> explain her self in this point, in the <hi>Secret Prayer</hi> on St. <hi>Andrew</hi>'s day: <hi>Sacrificium no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum,</hi> sayes the Priest, <hi>tibi Domine quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumus, beati Andreae Apostoli precatio sancta conciliat: ut in cujus honore so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemniter exhibetur, ejus meritis efficiatur acceptum. Per Dominum nostrum, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Orate, fratres, &amp;c. <hi>pag</hi> 26.</head>
                  <p>THe Priest having performed the duty of a publick Minister, in preparing, dedicating, and presenting to God the Father the foresaid Oblations; and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to mind his own unworthiness, he turns to the People, saying, <hi>Orate, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres.</hi>
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:63525:76"/> Thereby desiring them to ratify publickly by themselves, what he hath done in their name, which the People do, in saying <hi>Suscipiat Dominus, &amp;c.</hi> in a loud voice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Secreta. <hi>pag.</hi> 26.</head>
                  <p>AT last the Priest concludes all the Preparations belonging to this second part of the <hi>Mass,</hi> with a Secret Prayer, and therefore called <hi>Secreta.</hi> And having made all things ready for the grand Action of the Sacrifice, he recollects himself a little in private, to signify that we must joyn an interiour Spirit of devotion with the outward performance of our Piety.</p>
                  <p>Now, by this interiour Spirit of Piety are <hi>Christians</hi> properly distinguished from the <hi>Jews,</hi> who offered their Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with only outward Ceremonies; which caused God to reproach them by telling them, That their Sacrifices were in abomination to him: <hi>Ne offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratis ultra Sacrificium frustra, Incensum abominatio est mihi.—Solemnitates ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stras odivit anima mea; Isa. 1. 13, &amp;</hi> 14. At last the Priest ends this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:63525:77"/> Prayer in a loud voice, saying. <hi>Per omnia saeeula saeculorum;</hi> which the People ratify, by answering, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>SƲRSƲM CORDA, <hi>pag. 28. OR THE PREFACE TO THE CANON.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Preface is a kind of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, to stir up and prepare the Assistants to the main Action, in which the Sacrifice does properly consist. Hitherto the Priest hath been preparing himself, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the Bread and Wine. Now he endeavours to dispose the hearts and affections of the People, for the joynt offering up this Great Sacrifice, disengaging their thoughts from all Creatures and earthly incumbrances, saying, <hi>Sursum corda.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:63525:77"/>
               <p>Then gathering as it were the voices of the People, who answer him, that their hearts are raised, he addresses himself to God the Father with lofty expressions, publickly acknowledging the favours he alwayes and in all places bestows upon Mankind. And not to be wanting in any kind of praise for his inestimable benefits, he joyns himself with the Angels, Cherubins and Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins, who praise and adore God with an awfull reverence; and with them unites himself in <hi>Christ</hi> our Lord, as the common Father, and Head of both Men and Angels; by repeating the Hymn, <hi>Sanctus, Sanctus, Sanctus, &amp;c.</hi> which those Spirits sing incessantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne of God.</p>
               <p>At this Entry of the Sacrifice, we should all wish to see the Heavens open as they did to St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> since the Celestial Court comes down and waits about the Altar, as St. <hi>Chrysostom,</hi> St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> and St. <hi>Austin</hi> assure us. But to frame in our minds a lively <hi>Idaea</hi> of these Heavenly Spirits attending this Sacrifice, we should twice or thrice read over the fourth &amp; fifth Chapters of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:63525:78"/> St. <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Apocalypse,</hi> where there is a lively description of their waiting about the Throne of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> and about the <hi>Lamb</hi> that lies like a slain <hi>Victim</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the same Throne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:63525:78"/>
            <head>✚ THE THIRD PART, which is the CANON, OR ACTION OF THE SACRIFICE; As EXPIATORY. EUCHARISTICAL. IMPETRATORY, for the <hi>Living</hi> &amp; the <hi>Dead.</hi> HOLOCAUSTICAL. And comprehending the three essential conditions of a perfect Sacrifice. <hi>viz.</hi> The Destruction, Oblation, <hi>and</hi> Consummation of the <hi>Victim.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="summary">
               <head>Of the Canon of the <hi>Mass</hi> in general.</head>
               <p>THE word <hi>Canon</hi> is <hi>Greek,</hi> and here signifies a standing and settled rule for celebrating the Divine Mysteries. It is very ancient,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:63525:79"/> and there is not a word in it that sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours not of great Holiness and Piety. And the holy Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> assures us, <hi>Sess. 22. cap.</hi> 4. That it is made up of our Saviours very words, of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolical Traditions, and of the Decrees of Holy Bishops.</p>
               <p>Nor indeed could it well consist of words less weighty, since in all our Religion, there is no Action more holy, nor more acceptable to God, than the sacred Mystery of the Altar; which contains in short all what God hath done for us, and all the duties and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages we are to pay to him. As also it accomplisheth the strict union, which from all eternity he would have with Man, by the Mediation of <hi>Christ</hi> our Redeemer; who offering up himself to his Eternal Father, from his first En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the World, designed to himself divers ends in his Oblation, <hi>viz.</hi> the Homage he would pay him as to the Soveraign Being; The Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he hath been pleased to diversify his Sacrifice of the Altar, according to these divers ends and effects for which he designed it. And for the same reason
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:63525:79"/> did he ordain several sorts of Sacrifices in the Old Law, which were the types of the New. For <hi>all these things that befell unto them, were figures, 1 Cor.</hi> 10. 11.</p>
               <p>Nor is the Ordering of this <hi>Sacred Canon,</hi> (called <hi>Action</hi> by St. <hi>Denis,)</hi> less considerable than the words thereof. First it begins with the letter T, which represents to us the Cross and Passion of <hi>Christ,</hi> from whence it hath all its efficacy, betokened by the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Crosses made over the Oblations all along this third Part.</p>
               <p>It is also said in secret: First (as sayes <hi>Almarius lib. 3. c.</hi> 9. and <hi>Gemma lib. 1. c.</hi> 40.) to signify, that the ancient Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices lye hid in this of the New Law, as this Sacrifice lay formerly hid, in those of the Old Testament. But chiefly, as I conceive, to praise God, according to the example of <hi>Christ</hi> in the Blessed Sacrament. He speakes not a word, words are to mean too glorify an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite God. But to praise him by si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, is to pray him infinitely: In as much as thereby we acknowledge him infinitely Great, and that he cannot be praised enough, Wherefore the <hi>Psal.</hi> 64,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:63525:80"/> which begins with these words; <hi>An Hymn of praise becomes Thee, O God,</hi> hath in the original Text, <hi>Silence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Thee, O God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the Oblations and <hi>Victims,</hi> we are to offer according to the four ends of this Sacrifice; we need not provide for Bulls or Goats, like the <hi>Jews;</hi> Truths have succeeded figures. For if we rightly understand the secret of our Mysteries, we should offer the things that were signify'd by those Beasts; since that St. <hi>Austin</hi> assures us, That we have in our selves wherewith to make a Sacrifice: <hi>Noli,</hi> saith he, <hi>extrinsecus pecus quod mactes inquirere, habes in te quod occidas.</hi> And for the supply of what will still be wanting in our Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, let us take it from the infinite Satisfactions of <hi>Christ;</hi> since that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents himself to us at the Altar for that end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part_of_canon">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:63525:80"/>
               <head>I. Part of the Canon; Containing the GENERAL INTENTION Of the Church in this Sacrifice.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Te igitur, Clementissime, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 32.</head>
                  <p>HERE the Priest in the name of the whole <hi>Church</hi> begins the great Action of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, addresses himself to God the Father, and makes an humble suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to him, through <hi>Christ</hi> our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour, that he would accept of what he is now to do, and give a blessing to his Action; to the end the Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may become the <hi>Victim</hi> of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice he is now about to offer. First, for the whole Church throughout the World. Next, at the <hi>Memento,</hi> for such living members thereof, as he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to pray for in particular. And lastly, for all then present at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, as concurring with the Saints
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:63525:81"/> in Heaven, mentioned at the Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning <hi>Communicantes,</hi> whose inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession he joyns with that of <hi>Christ,</hi> and so concludes with <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part_of_canon">
               <head>II. Part of the Canon; Answering to the SACRIFICE OF EXPIATION &amp; to the DESTRUCTION OF THE VICTIM In the Old Law.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Hanc igitur oblationem,</hi> p. 34.</head>
                  <p>HERE the Priest spreads his hands over the Host and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice. Now, to understand this Ceremony, we must know, That God commanded <hi>Aaron (Levit.</hi> 16. 20.) to sacrifice a Goat for the expiation of the sins of the People, in this manner. First he bade him spread his hands over the Goat; thereby to signify that he lay'd upon him the sins of all the People; and then to turn him out into the Wilderness, there to be devoured by wild Beasts.</p>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:63525:81"/>
                  <p>By this Goat, the <hi>Church</hi> hath ever understood our Saviour <hi>Christ,</hi> who taking upon himself the sins of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, was turned out of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> crucified in the desert place of Mount <hi>Calvary</hi> by the <hi>Jews,</hi> herein as bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous as wilde Beasts. So here the Bread and Wine, over which the Priest spreads his hands, are the <hi>Victims</hi> upon which he layes as it were both his own and the sins of the People, that it may be destroy'd in Sacrifice, in lieu of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Thereby to acknowledge our selves worthy of death; Death being the punishment wherewith God threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Adam</hi> in case he sinned.</p>
                  <p>Nay, even the <hi>Egyptians</hi> instructed by the light of Nature only, were of the same mind, when they stampt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their <hi>Victim</hi> the picture of a Slave stabbing himself, as we imprint on the Host <hi>Christ</hi> crucified. <hi>Apud Aegyptios Victima inurebatur sigillo quodam, in qua effigies erat Servi seipfum gladio confodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entis. Plut. in Isiod. &amp; Osi.</hi> To insorm all the World that God sparing Man, gave him leave to sacrifice other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in his place, and to charge them with his sin and punishment.</p>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:63525:82"/>
                  <p>With this Ceremony of holding his hand over the Oblations, the Priest joyns words to the same purpose; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching God to be appeased by this Oblation of our bondage, as he calls it. To signify, that by our sins we become slaves of the Divel, as the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians</hi> represented it by their figure of a slave. He begs of him likewise to grant us peace, wars and troubles being usually the effects of sin: and to free us from damnation, of which sin is the only cause.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Quam oblationem, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 36.</head>
                  <p>NOw the Priest beseeches God, that this Oblation or <hi>Victim,</hi> load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as it were with our sins, may be receiv'd, and be acceptable to him, and be changed into the Body and Bloud of <hi>Christ</hi> his Son, in vertue of the words of Consecration; so to be sacrifized in place of guilty Man. For thus did God's Providence substituted a Ram, which was the figure of <hi>Christ,</hi> instead of the life of <hi>Isaack,</hi> when his Father <hi>Abraham</hi> was about to sacrifice him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. 13.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part_of_canon">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:63525:82"/>
               <head>✚ THE CONSECRATION and ELEVATION Of the BODY AND BLOUD <hi>OF CHRIST.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS the Ram supply'd the place of <hi>Isaack,</hi> and the Goat devoured in the Wilderness the place of the People; in the very same manner does <hi>Christ</hi> here supply the place of guilty Man, by the division of his Body and Bloud in the Consecration. For the Holy Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> hath defined <hi>(Sess. 22. cap.</hi> 22.) That this is a Propitiatory or Expiatory Sacrifice. So that <hi>God the Father being moved and fully satisfied by this Oblation, grants us grace, and the gift of Penance, in virtue of which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits sins, though never so great and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous.</hi> And as in the Consecration of the Chalice, <hi>Christ</hi> said that <hi>his Bloud was shed</hi> and offered <hi>for the remission of
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:63525:83"/> sins; Matth.</hi> 16. 28. the Priest daysy repeats <hi>Christ</hi>'s own words in his name. As also at the first <hi>Memento,</hi> the Priest sayes, We offer this Sacrifice <hi>for the Redemption of our Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet it is not known to every one how this Expiation is performed; So won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull a way hath <hi>Christ</hi> chosen, to put himself in the sight of his Father, in a condition of a continual object of Propitiation for our sins: For knowing there is nothing so proper to extinguish the fire of God's wrath as penance; he puts himself in the condition of a Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, hid under the <hi>species</hi> of Bread and Wine. Nay, foreseeing that to the World's end there will be sinners, he likewise will remain in that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the said end of the World, to allay his Fathers wrath, and disarm as it were his Divine Justice.</p>
               <p>The bloudy Sacrifice he offered on Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> was a publick penance he underwent for the sins of the whole World, because he took upon him the sins of all Mankind, and look'd upon himself as guilty of a publick malice. This example of <hi>Christ</hi> did St. <hi>Charles Boromeus</hi> follow, when he stood
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:63525:83"/> like a publick Penitent with a halter about his neck, to disarm God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty incensed against the People of <hi>Milan,</hi> who with tears and sighs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd likewise the example of their holy Pastor. The Passion then of our Saviour on the Cross was a publick pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: but the mild and unbloudy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, which he offers dayly upon the Church Altars, is a secret penance, which he undergoes for his members here on Earth. This we should call to mind in the time of <hi>Mass</hi> after the Consecration.</p>
               <p>And this Part of the <hi>Canon</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Hanc igitur Oblationem,</hi> and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Consecration, answers to the third and essential Condition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in a true Sacrifice; <hi>viz.</hi> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction and death of the <hi>Victim.</hi> For three things are to be consider'd in the Consecration: 1. The Destruction of the substance of Bread and Wine to the honour of God: 2. The real Presence of <hi>Christ</hi> taking its place: 3. A mystical kind of death in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of his Body and Blood u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited by Concomitance, and this in vertue of the words of Consecration, as
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:63525:84"/> St. <hi>Gregory of Nazianzen</hi> assures us: <hi>Incruenta sectione, Corpus &amp; Sanguinem Domini cum secas, vocem adhibens pro gladio, Ep. 240. ad Amphl.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="practical_directions">
                  <head>PRACTICAL DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> IN the mean time that the Priest is at this part of the <hi>Canon,</hi> by an Act of Faith acknowledge your self a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and so lyable to the Divine Justice for a multitude of offences by you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, against his Divine Majesty.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Be truely sorrowful for them; offer <hi>Victims</hi> in satisfaction, and instead of a Calf which God commanded to be offered for expiation of sin, <hi>Levit. 4.</hi> offer all the pains and sufferings of your Body. In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stead of Turtles commanded in the same place, offer the retirements, the sighs, and groans of a penitent heart, whereof these Birds are the symbol. Instead of salt, commanded in the second chapter, endeavour to avoid sin for the future, and preserve your self from its corruption. And because in the Sacrifice for the Expiation of sin, God would have neither Oyl, nor incense offered to him, <hi>Levit. 4.</hi> (they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the symbols of earthly joyes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures)
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:63525:84"/> debar your self dayly of some kind of pleasure, because you dayly sin.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> But seeing evidently, that this your payment comes short of your debts and trespasses, even when you have done your utmost endeavour; in supply of what is wanting to your payment, present to our offended God the sufferings of his Saints; but offer especially this pretious <hi>Victim</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi>'s Body in a full discharge of your debts, saying with the Devout St. <hi>Bernard: De te Domine suppleo, quod minus habeo; Serm. 1. de Epiph. in med.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part_of_canon">
               <head>III. Part of the Canon; Answering to the SACRIFICE OF THANKSGIVING, And to the OBLATION OF THE VICTIM In the Old Law.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Ʋnde &amp; memores, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 38.</head>
                  <p>HEre the Priest in the name of all the <hi>Church</hi> performs the Act of Oblation of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Victim</hi> of the Body and Bloud of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:63525:85"/>
                     <hi>Christ,</hi> as the chiefest part of the <hi>Mass,</hi> which being a Sacrifice doth necessarily suppose it; for there is no Sacrifice without Oblation, and this Oblation is the thing principally intended in the <hi>Mass,</hi> and is the noblest function belonging to Priesthood, according to the words of the Apostle: <hi>Every High-Priest taken from among Men, is appointed for Men to those things that appertain to God, that he may offer gifts and Sacrifices for sin, Hebr.</hi> 5. 1.</p>
                  <p>And this Solemn Action of Offering, is done by the Priest and all the People, in remembrance of Thanksgiving for all God's innumerable favours bestow'd upon us. For true Piety consists in the Soul's grateful acknowledgement: <hi>Dei cultus in hoc maxime constitutus est, ut anima ei non sit ingrata; St. Aug. lib. de Spir. &amp; Lit. e.</hi> 11. Nay, this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery, which St. <hi>Austin</hi> in the same place calls a True and Wonderful Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice; <hi>Verissimum &amp; singulare Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium,</hi> is named <hi>Eucharisi,</hi> which sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>Thansgiving:</hi> Because here <hi>Christ</hi> as our sacrified <hi>Victim,</hi> gives Thanks to God the Father, <hi>Gratias agens, 1 Cor.</hi> 11. 41. for all his benefits bestow'd
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:63525:85"/> upon us, knowing our insufficiency in this behalf.</p>
                  <p>For we have received from his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful hand several sorts of benefits, for which we are to return him thanks. First we have received the benefits of Nature in those of our Body, such as our health, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Those of our Soul, as Wit and Understanding. And those of Fortune, as Honour and Wealth. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, we have received Supernatural favours, such as relate to Everlasting Happiness, of which <hi>Christ</hi>'s merits dayly apply'd to us, are an inexhaustable Treasure.</p>
                  <p>Now, in our most Divine Sacrifice of the Altar, we offer a thing of a far greater value than are all these, or what other Blessings God the Father hath given us; because we offer up to him his very Son, whom he also gave us, that by this Oblation, we might repay whatsoever we owe him. Thus blessing himself, the Priest ends this part of the <hi>Canon</hi> with <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="practical_directions">
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:63525:86"/>
                  <head>PRACTICAL DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>BY an Act of Faith, acknowledge that all the benefits, graces, and favours you enjoy, either in Body or Soul, are poured down upon you, from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhaustible Source of God's meer Liberality.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. <hi>Shew some kind of gratitude in requital; First in prizing and publishing God's benefits: In presenting our selves, as a Votive Table hung up at his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, in a sign and memorial to the whole World of the obligations we have to him. Finally, in making the best use of them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. <hi>But knowing that though we should melt away into these affections of gratitude; yet this kind of Thanksgiving would still be too mean to countervail the Divine favours, we here offer up</hi> Christ, <hi>in supply of what is wanting on our part.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part_of_canon">
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:63525:86"/>
               <head>IV. Part of the Canon; Answering to the IMPETRATORY SACRIFICE, OR SECOND PEACE-OFFERING In the Old Law.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The <hi>Memento</hi> for the Dead. <hi>pag.</hi> 40.</head>
                  <p>AS our bountiful Saviour did him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self apply the first fruits of his Passion to the Souls in <hi>Limbo,</hi> or <hi>Purgatory,</hi> at his descent into Hell; so here the Priest does likewise in the name of all the <hi>Church,</hi> offer the very same Body and Bloud of <hi>Christ,</hi> as a powerful <hi>Victim</hi> for obtaining relief and comfort for the penitent Souls in <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, Zach.</hi> 9. 10.</p>
                  <p>These prayers for the Souls in <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> answer to the Sacrifices of the Old Law offered for the Dead among the <hi>Jews.</hi> For the Holy and valiant Souldier <hi>Judas Macchabaeus,</hi> sent great
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:63525:87"/> sums of Money to <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> to have Sacrifices offered in the Temple for the Souls of the Dead, 2 <hi>Macchab.</hi> 12. 42.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Nobis quoque peccatoribus, &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 40.</head>
                  <p>HAving pray'd for the Dead, as Christian Charity prompts us, first to assist those that are more in distress, and less able to help themselves: The Priest now with the People petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Living, offer an Impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Sacrifice, to the end they may obtain new favours and blessings from God, in consideration of his dear Son, whom they conjointly present to him, as an Advocate who intercedes for us: <hi>Interpellat pro nobis, Rom.</hi> 8. 34. Thus <hi>David</hi> offered a Sacrifice of <hi>Peace-Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> for the divertion of the Plague, and he obtained his petition; 2 <hi>Reg. 24. 25. Onias</hi> likewise offered a Sacrifice for the recovery of <hi>Heliodorus</hi>'s Life, and it was granted to him; 2 <hi>Mach.</hi> 3. 32.</p>
                  <p>If then the offering of a Lamb or Kid, was so prevalent a means to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from God the thing desired; how
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:63525:87"/> much greater efficacy is there in offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him his very Son? If God made such promises to <hi>Abraham,</hi> in regard of the sole will he had to sacrifise his Son; what benefits and graces will he bestow on those that offer to him his only begotten Son? What favours will he not grant? Nay, what can we ask with such a present, which he will not give?</p>
                  <p>The Faithfull knock their breast in making this address to God; to signify that they acknowledge themselves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of these favours they beg for. Yet they beseech God in virtue of the <hi>Church Militant</hi> and <hi>Triumphant</hi> to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their defects, by the Intercession of these Great Saints here named, and to make them at last partakers of their company in Heaven: and so conclude their petition, <hi>Through Christ our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="practical_directions">
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:63525:88"/>
                  <head>PRACTICAL DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>ACknowledge on the one side the inexhaustible riches of God; and on the other our extream poverty, who having nothing, stand in need of all things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. <hi>Being pressed with our wants, let us approach the gates of this God so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding rich, and in all humility present him our petitions. Let us beg of him an innocent and undefiled Life, such as is represented to us by the unspotted Lamb, which God commanded should be offered to him,</hi> Levit. 3. 7. 1. <hi>Let us beg of this Rich Lord the Light of Truth, and the cheerfulness of an upright Conscience, signify'd by the Oyl and Wine. As also grace to avoid the giving of scandal, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented by the Incense offered in the Law,</hi> Levit. 2.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. <hi>Considering that our importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties have nothing in them, to enforce his Bounty to open his hands upon us, and dispense his Treasuries, let us in supply present to him the unspotted Lamb, lying
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:63525:88"/> upon the Altar: and doubtless our peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will not be rejected. For what he will not give to us, he will grant to him, in whose name we are promised not to be deny'd,</hi> John 14. 13.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part_of_canon">
               <head>V. Part of the Canon; Answering to the SACRIFICE OF HOLOCAUST, And to the CONSUMMATION OF THE VICTIM In the Old Law.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Per quem haec Domine, &amp;c.</hi> p. 42.</head>
                  <p>HEre the Priest comes to the most noble Action of Religion; where in the name of all the <hi>Church,</hi> he makes an Holocaustical Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, to acknowledge thereby the Supream Soveraignty of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the first Principle, not only of all Creatures, but of the Divine Persons also. To proclaim his own and the People's nothingness and entire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency on him: wherefore the Priest
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:63525:89"/> in the beginning of this Grand Action, makes mention of the Creation and Preservation in these words, <hi>Semper bona creas.</hi> But the better to shew with what awe he speaks to his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Creatour, he holds up <hi>Christ,</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Per quem hac, Domine, &amp;c.</hi> as not daring to speak immediatly to God.</p>
                  <p>In the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> the Destruction of the <hi>Victim</hi> was not the Principal, though the most sensible part of the Sacrifice, being performed by the <hi>Levites</hi> only, and not by the Priests, and that too in the Court of the Temple, and not in the place next to the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary. But as the most considerable part was the Consummation of the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctim</hi> devoured by the flames ascending up towards Heaven; so this part of the <hi>Mass,</hi> as answering to that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>summation, is the noblest, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently deserves our attention and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, as accomplishing the fifth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition required to the perfection of a Sacrifice.</p>
                  <p>But where then is the fire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume this <hi>Holocaust?</hi> First it is not neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary that the Figure and the Thing fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured agree in all things, as the Learned
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:63525:89"/>
                     <hi>Estius</hi> assures us: <hi>Non omnia debent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruere inter figuram &amp; rem figuratam; sed satis est, si in genere &amp; in fine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniant; Est. in cap. 3. Levitici.</hi> Next, St. <hi>Paul</hi> easily resolves this question, when he tells us; That <hi>our God is a consuming fire, Hebr.</hi> 12. 29.</p>
                  <p>Now this material fire required in the Old Law, was but a figure and symbol of the sacred fire of Charity, with which we <hi>Christians</hi> offer up the Holocaust of Love upon the burning Altar of our hearts. And with this Holy fire of inflaming Charity, it is, that <hi>Christ,</hi> by the hands of the Priest, offers up himself a most pure, a most holy, and a most acceptable Holocaust to God the Father.</p>
                  <p>At the words, <hi>Per quem haec omnia, &amp;c.</hi> the Priest lifting up both the Host and the Chalice together, does in the name of all the Assistants, make a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn protestation to God the Father, that the <hi>Sacred Victim</hi> here on the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and all the perfections it contains, proceed originally from him, by this his Son. By whom, as by the chief Priest, he dayly produces it by a kind of Creation at the words of Consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:63525:90"/> and by an enlivening Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, enricheth it with all sorts of Blessings; and so graciously pleased to bestow it upon us, as a Divine food suited to our immortal Souls.</p>
                  <p>Then again, knowing that God the Father receives nothing from us im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly, but by <hi>Christ</hi> as our Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour; we pay him in acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of these Blessings, all Homage, Glory, and Praise; by, with, and in <hi>Christ,</hi> for ever and ever: which solemn acknowledgement the People ratify, by answering aloud, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here I cannot but admire the Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Artifice of my Saviour's Love; who to honour God the Father in a way worthy of him, and to give te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of his Soveraign power over all Creatures, dyes every day with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dying; and by a sweet and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Immolation of himself (though not ceasing to live) remains in a condition of death: As St. <hi>John</hi> saw <hi>the Lamb lying as dead in his sight; Apoc.</hi> 5. 6. He knows that the Divine Majesty of his Father is to be acknowledged as such by an Illustrious <hi>Victim.</hi> And that he holds not himself sufficiently
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:63525:90"/> honoured, unless he sees a <hi>Victim</hi> as great and as holy as himself, lying at his feet in a dying posture; whose dumb voice, declares in all ages his Father's Soveraignty, and the dependency of all Creatures upon him.</p>
                  <p>What greater annihilation! or more profound humiliation can one imagine! than to see an immortal God alwayes living, and yet alwayes in a condition of death?</p>
                  <p>We may then boldly say, that the Priest here offers an Holocaust worthy of the Infinite Majesty of God. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause this <hi>Man-God</hi> or <hi>God-Man,</hi> sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiseth himself continually and for ever. So that if by the Incarnation, we are oblidged to God for giving us a God, the same God receives again from us a God at the Altar. And thus is there an equality betwixt Gift, and the return made for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pater noster, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 42.</head>
                  <p>THe Priest at the lifting up the Host and the Chalice, having privatly given to God all honour and glory; now breaks forth into a publick decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:63525:91"/> of the same: And yet out of a profound respect and awe, not daring to speak to God with words of his own framing, he makes his addresses to the Eternal Father, in the very words of his beloved Son, saying in a loud voice, <hi>Pater noster.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And for as much as in the first words of this Divine Prayer we call God our Father; the Priest considering the great honour we receive in this Title, and our own unworthiness to be admitted to it, he declares that if he presumes to call God Father, it is because that <hi>Christ</hi> himself hath commanded and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed such a form of words.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Libera nos quaesumus, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 44.</head>
                  <p>AS the words <hi>Praeceptis salutaribus moniti, &amp;c.</hi> are a Preface to the <hi>Pater noster;</hi> so these words <hi>Libera nos, &amp;c.</hi> are as it were an Epilogue, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a continuation of the same <hi>Pater noster,</hi> being in the nature of an eighth Petition thereto annexed. For <hi>Amen</hi> is not answer'd by the People at the end of the <hi>Pater noster:</hi> And this eighth Petition or Prayer, is to beg of God
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:63525:91"/> the Father <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> by the intercession of all his Saints, so as by the Mediation of <hi>Christ</hi> his Son, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Per Dominum nostrum, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this word <hi>Peace,</hi> is understood all things belonging to salvation: <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine pacis apud Hebraeos, fere omne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp; quidquid ad salutem pertinet, comprehenditur; Estius in cap. 3. Levit.</hi> And this Peace is the chief effect and the main fruit of the Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross,</hi> in reconciling God and Man, and setling peace between Heaven and Earth divided by the sin of <hi>Adam.</hi> In token of which peace, he makes the sign of the <hi>Cross</hi> in kissing the <hi>Patene.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, to show that this <hi>Peace</hi> is the main fruit of the Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross,</hi> apply'd to us by that of the <hi>Altar:</hi> it is manifest out of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who fore-telling the coming of <hi>Christ,</hi> stile him the Prince of Peace: <hi>Princeps pacis, Isa.</hi> 9. 6. And this Peace none could purchase for us or give to us, but <hi>Christ</hi> alone. This Peace it is which the Patriarks so long sighed after: <hi>Suscipiant montes pacem, Psal.</hi> 71. This Peace it is which the Angels sung at his Birth: <hi>Pax hominibus bonae vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:63525:92"/> Luc.</hi> 2. This Peace it is which he gave to his Disciples, as a pledge of his Love before he went to his Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: <hi>Pacem relinquo vobis, Pacem meam do vobis, Joan.</hi> 16. In fine, this Peace it is, which he gave them at his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection, as the first effusion of his Glory, and the greatest reward of all his labours, saying thrice; <hi>Pax vobis, Joan.</hi> 20.</p>
                  <p>At last, the Priest supposing that God will not deny us, what we have begg'd of him, in the Person, in the Name, and even in the very words of his Son, he divides the <hi>Sacred Host</hi> into three parts, saying at the same time: <hi>Through the same our Lord</hi> Jesus Christ <hi>thy Son, who being God, liveth and reigneth with thee in the Ʋnity of the Holy Ghost, world without end.</hi> And so in a loud voice concludes and closeth the Action of the Sacrifice with <hi>Per omnia saecula saeculorum:</hi> to which the People answer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pax Domini sit, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 44.</head>
                  <p>HEre the Priest with one part of the Consecrated <hi>Host,</hi> makes three
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:63525:92"/> crosses over the Chalice, saying at the same time: <hi>The Peace of the Lord be with you.</hi> With this solemn Blessing of Peace over the People, represented by the Water in the Chalice, he does as it were seal up the Action of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. Thus <hi>Melchisedeck</hi> having of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered his Sacrifice of Bread and Wine, blessed <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his Men; <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="practical_directions">
                  <head>PRACTICAL DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>BY a lively Act of Faith, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Soveraignty of God, as being the Author both of our Creation and Preservation, and that we in all things depend upon him, who is the sole inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Being.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. <hi>In acknowledgement of which So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, we must offer him Sacrifice as the supream Homage due to his Divine Majesty. And because he commanded three sorts of things,</hi> viz. <hi>Beasts, Birds, and Liquours to be entirely burnt and destory'd in honour of himself;</hi> Levit. 1. <hi>we should likewise present our selves before his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and offer up our Lives and Estates
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:63525:93"/> as Victims wholly prepared to be immola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and consumed in a perfect Holocaust, when ever his Honour shall require it, in testimony that we hold them all of him. For otherwise, it were to present to God an external figure, destitute of the Truth we pretend to.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>III. <hi>Yet all this not being an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage proportionable to his Greatness; we must above all, substitute</hi> Christ <hi>here my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stically immolated on the Altar, protest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that his Divine Majesty deserves to have so precious a Life consecrated to his Honour.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <pb n="173" facs="tcp:63525:93"/>
            <head>✚ THE FOURTH PART, which is the COMMUNION OF THE EUCHARIST. Answering to the sixth and essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial condition required in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of <hi>Peace-Offerings</hi> in the Old Law; <hi>viz.</hi> THE COMMUNION Of the <hi>Victim.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of this Communion in general.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Action of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice being ended, the Priest and the People proceed to the receiving of the Sacrament. But for as much as in the Sacrifices of <hi>Peace-Offerings,</hi> a part of the <hi>Victim</hi> was set aside for the Offerers,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:63525:94"/> remains that we now speak of <hi>Christ;</hi> not as a Sacrifice, but as a Sacrament; our blessed Saviour out of his great love, having associated two subjects, which have so small relation each to other.</p>
               <p>For as it is a Sacrament, it preserves the life of a <hi>Christian;</hi> and as it is a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, it engageth him to death. <hi>Christ</hi> upon the Altar, being as well our food as our <hi>Victim,</hi> where he offers up himself to his Father as an innocent Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and gives himself to the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as a delicious nourishment: And thus he satisfies both his Father and his Children, who are nourished with that Bloud, with which they were begotten upon the <hi>Cross;</hi> that so they might be preserved by the same Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple that gave them life.</p>
               <p>Here God the Father having gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously accepted of our Divine <hi>Victim</hi> in a Sacrifice, liberally returns it to us in a Sacrament, and bids us, as it were, feast and rejoyce before him: <hi>Date, &amp; dabitur vobis, Luc.</hi> 6. 30. Hence we may see the main difference between a Sacrifice and a Sacrament; which is, that in the Sacrifice Men give to God, and in the Sacrament God gives to Man.</p>
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:63525:94"/>
               <p>In this fourth and Sacramental part of the <hi>Mass,</hi> are apply'd to us the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits both of the Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross,</hi> and of the <hi>Altar;</hi> which last, here sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies what was wanting to the first, since none then did eat of <hi>Christ</hi>'s mortal Body after the Consummation and surrending his life. So that some of the figures of the Old Law were not fulfilled in the Sacrifice of the <hi>Cross.</hi> For the eating and Communion of the <hi>Victim</hi> did alwayes succeed to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>summation of it, in the Sacrifices of Peace-Offerings.</p>
               <p>Now the Communion of the <hi>Victim</hi> is further evidenced in sundry Texts of Scripture. The example of the Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Lamb, is uncontestable; for after it had been sacrifised by the whole mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, <hi>Immolabit eum universa multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo, Exod.</hi> 12. 6. it was eaten by them. In this Lamb, two things relating to this present purpose, are to be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. First the immolation of it, which was a figure of <hi>Christ</hi> on the <hi>Cross.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the eating of it, which was a figure of <hi>Christ</hi> in the <hi>Eucharist.</hi> And this figure seems so clear, so pat, and so convincing as to the Sacrifice of
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:63525:95"/> the <hi>Altar,</hi> that I see not what can be rationally answered to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; <hi>Christ</hi> himself, approving it such, by his eating the Paschal Lamb with his Disciples, immediately before the Institution of the <hi>Eucharist.</hi> Let us therefore compare the figures of the Old Law, with the present truth of the New.</p>
               <p>But before we come to the actual Collation of them, it will not be amiss to make this short reflection. That since the <hi>Eucharist</hi> is the Bread that fattens Souls, as it is termed in the Church Office, <hi>Pinguis est panis Christi:</hi> How it comes to pass, that <hi>Christians</hi> draw so little fruit from so Divine a food, if we except a small number of Souls, in whom the above-said words are very<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd. Now if we examine the cause of this great misfortune, I take it to proceed from the want of a due prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is a kind of prophaning <hi>the Dreadfull Host,</hi> as the Church terms it. And indeed seeing the Son of God comprehends all his Graces and Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings in this Sacrament, we ought to come with real and solid dispositions of mind to receive him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:63525:95"/>
               <head>Haec commixtio &amp; Consecratio, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 44.</head>
               <p>HEre begins the Sacramental part of the <hi>Mass,</hi> by a kind of a new Consecration, arising from the exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour mingling of the Body and Bloud of <hi>Christ</hi> together, which is performed by the Priest's dropping a particle of the Host into the Chalice.</p>
               <p>Now this Consecration is but an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour kind of Mysterious sanctification: For in the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the Apostle St. <hi>James,</hi> where this Ceremony is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, we read these words, <hi>Ʋnitum est, &amp; sanctificatum.</hi> As therefore by the first Consecration is signify'd the Mystery of a Sacrifice, in the separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>species;</hi> so likewise in this second kind of Consecration, is signify'd the Mystery of a Sacrament, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the same <hi>species.</hi> From this Commixtion then ariseth a new kind of Consecration, in that the <hi>species,</hi> which by their division represented the death and Passion of <hi>Christ,</hi> do now by their conjunction represent his Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, where his sacred flesh was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:63525:96"/> united to his Sacred bloud. <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius lib. 3. c.</hi> 31.</p>
               <p>This new Consecration signifies not only the Resurrection of <hi>Christ,</hi> but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise that of the Faithfull (represent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Water mixt with the Wine in the Chalice,) to whom he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised Glory and Immortality. For the chief effect of this Celestial Food, is to preserve us from eternal death, and assure us of Life: <hi>He that eats my Flesh,</hi> saith Christ, <hi>shall live for ever, John</hi> 6. 55. In these words <hi>Christ</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageth himself by a solemn promise to raise us from the dead, by eating this ever to be adored Flesh; and for this reason the Holy Fathers call it some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Seed of Immortality, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Earnest of Glory, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Antidote of Death.</p>
               <p>Now, the Mystery signify'd by this Commixtion was figured in the Old Law, by a sprig of <hi>Hysop</hi> dipt in the bloud of the Paschal Lamb, wherewith all that were marked, were preserv'd from temporal death, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 22.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:63525:96"/>
               <head>Agnus Dei, qui, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 44.</head>
               <p>HEre the Priest bowing with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found respect, addresses himself no more to God the Father, as he did at the beginning of the <hi>Canon,</hi> in the words, <hi>Te igitur, Clementissime Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c.</hi> pag. 32. but to <hi>Christ</hi> his Son, saying to him <hi>Agnus Dei, qui, &amp;c.</hi> p. 44. and this and the following addresses made all to <hi>Christ</hi> and not to God the Father, are a strong argument to prove that the Action of the Sacrifice is ended. For all the Prayers in the Sacrifice are directed to God the Father, whereas now they are all directed to <hi>Christ</hi> his Blessed Son.</p>
               <p>For as much as sin is the obstacle to the blessed Life we expect, the Priest in the name of all the People, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that we are never without sin in this Life, that it is <hi>Christ</hi> who takes it away, implores his Divine mercy, by this act of Adoration and penance, of which the Preacher <hi>John the Baptist</hi> gave us assurance, when he said, <hi>Behold the Lamb of God, behold him who takes away the sins of the World, John</hi> 1. 29.</p>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:63525:97"/>
               <p>Innocency then is the first disposition in order to the worthy eating of this Food of Angels. And this was figured to us in the <hi>Ʋnlevened bread</hi> commanded by God to be eaten with the flesh of the Paschal Lamb, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 8. For <hi>leven</hi> is a symbole of sin and malice, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> himself hath explained it, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Let us feast therefore, not in the leven of corruption and malice, but in the azims of sincerity and truth, 1 Cor.</hi> 5. 7. But the Paschal Lamb was not eaten with only unleven bread, but with <hi>wild lettices</hi> also, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 8. to signify to us the wholsom bitterness of penance, wherewith the Faithfull are to prepare themselves to the Communion, cleansing our Souls by penance, from the sinful humours gathered together in our hearts, by the disorders of our lives: <hi>Ʋt ipsa amaritudo poenitentiae, abstergat a mentis stomacho, perversae humorem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae, St. Greg. Hom.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>This purity of Conscience required for the due receiving of the Virginal flesh of <hi>Christ,</hi> was further pointed out to us in the fall of the <hi>Manna.</hi> For we read in the Holy Scripture, that there fell in the night a dew upon the field,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:63525:97"/> and upon that dew the <hi>Manna: Jacuit ros per circuitum castrorum, Exod.</hi> 16. 13. This dew was like a clean linning to receive it, that it might not be soiled in falling upon the ground. By this dew is represented God's Grace, and by the <hi>Manna</hi> the Sacred Body of <hi>Christ</hi> received upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Domine Jesu Christe, qui, &amp;c.</hi> p. 46.</head>
               <p>HEre the Priest sayes a Prayer to beg Peace, Charity, and Union with our Neighbour, according to that of our Saviour, <hi>Be thou reconciled to thy Brother, before thou comest to the Altar, Matth.</hi> 5. 25. And the sign of this bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Charity, is a Kiss given to the <hi>Deacon</hi> at <hi>High-Masse,</hi> and which he should give to the rest of the Faithful with a <hi>Pax.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Chrysostom</hi> gives a good reason for this Ceremony: <hi>It is,</hi> saith he, <hi>because we are the Temples of</hi> Christ, <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do we kiss the door of the Temple, Hom. 3. in Ep. 2. ad Cor.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:63525:98"/>
               <p>This Charitable disposition was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably well figured out to us, in the <hi>Jews eating the bowels of the Paschal Lamb, Exod.</hi> 12. 9. For the bowels denote to us the tender love of Charity we ought to have for our Neighbour, and which St <hi>Paul</hi> bore to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> when he said; <hi>I wish you all in the bowels of</hi> Christ, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. 8. The bowels are not only the symbol and seat of Love, but that of most tender love, which Mothers have for their Children.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Masses</hi> for the Dead, the <hi>Pax</hi> is not given, because the Dead being no more among us, we need not pray that we may live in peace with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Domine Jesu Christe, Fili, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 46.</head>
               <p>BY this Prayer the Priest beseeches <hi>Christ</hi> to strike in him an holy fear, that he may not rashly approach this Sacred Table, without such prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as becomes his Divine Majesty.</p>
               <p>Holy History tell us 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. 7. that <hi>David</hi> being resolved to bring the <hi>Ark of the Covenant</hi> into his City, and
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:63525:98"/> having to that end placed it upon a chariot, where through the unrullness of the Beasts, being ready to fal, <hi>Oza</hi> standing by, stretcht out his hand to uphold it; but God immediately punished him for his rashness <hi>super te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meritate,</hi> he falling down dead in the place. Now the remembrance of this and the like punishments, strikes a just fear into holy Souls; and makes the Priest to beg that he may be delivered from all dangers, considering the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion between the purity of his heart, and that of this <hi>Dreadful Host.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Perceptio Corporis tui, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 48.</head>
               <p>IN this Prayer the Priest begs of <hi>Christ</hi> that he may not by abusing his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Body, incur the heavy judgments he layes upon those that contemn the most dreadful of our Mysteries.</p>
               <p>We have a lively figure of such abuses in the Old Law, where the human hopes and trust, reposed by the <hi>Jews</hi> in the <hi>Ark of the Covenant,</hi> sets forth to us the manner of many <hi>Christians</hi> deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:63525:99"/> with the Blessed <hi>Eucharist.</hi> For in the first book of <hi>Kings</hi> Chap. the fourth we read, That the <hi>Jews</hi> finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves defeated by the <hi>Philistins;</hi> the Elders of the People said among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves: <hi>Why hath the Lord struck us by the hands of the Philistins? let us have the Ark of the Covenant brought among us, that it may preserve us from our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, 1 Reg. c.</hi> 4. 3. Hereupon they caused it to be brought into the Camp: Yet nevertheless the <hi>Ark</hi> it self with the two Priests that brought it, was taken, the <hi>Jews</hi> again defeated, and thirty thousand of them slain upon the place.</p>
               <p>Now, these unexpected misfortunes befell the <hi>Jews</hi> for their making use of the <hi>Ark</hi> as an ordinary thing, and not as the Throne of the Living God. And because they did not humble themselves after their first defeat, nor had recourse to prayer, and fasting, as <hi>Hester</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith</hi> had in the like occasions. Finally, because they never consulted the <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifes</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> to know whether he would be pleased to deliver them by this, or by some other means. Not unlike to those <hi>Jews,</hi> there are too
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:63525:99"/> many among <hi>Christians,</hi> that abuse the <hi>Holy Eucharist</hi> under pretence of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing it. They seemingly bear a great respect to <hi>Christ,</hi> and desire his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence to defend them against their spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual enemies; but they neglect to prepare themselves worthily for his coming, by avoiding all dangerous oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions of displeasing him, by repressing their passions and vitious habits, and by deploring their sins before him.</p>
               <p>As for the two <hi>Priests,</hi> it is marked in Sacred Scripture that they were wicked and coveteous, and sought more to please the People than God: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we see they did countenance and authorise the Peoples desire in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them the <hi>Ark.</hi> Those blind and self-interressed Priests, led this blind and careless People. The one and the other put their trust in the <hi>Ark,</hi> and the one and the other are overcome and slain at last. Thus are painted to us the sad successes of indiscreet and rash Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:63525:100"/>
               <head>Domine, non sum dignus, &amp;c. pag. 48.</head>
               <p>HEre the Priest reflects on the humble faith of the <hi>Centurion,</hi> how acceptable it was to <hi>Christ,</hi> when of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to visit him, he reply'd; <hi>Lord, I am not worthy, &amp;c.</hi> Imitating there in the example of <hi>David,</hi> when he said; <hi>Quomodo ingredietur ad me Arca Domini: 2 Reg.</hi> 6. 9. showing by this their words, that in this High Mystery our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing must become the <hi>Victim</hi> of our Faith.</p>
               <p>This Heroick Act of Faith, was ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified in the <hi>Jews</hi> eating the Head of the <hi>Paschal Lamb, Exod.</hi> 12. 8. For <hi>the Head of Christ, is God,</hi> saith Saint <hi>Gregory; so that to eat the Head of the Lamb, is to consider with a lively Faith, that Christ is God; Hom. 22. in Evang.</hi> And therefore with profound reverence doth the Priest say; <hi>Domine, non sum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnus, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:63525:100"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Corpus Domini nostri, &amp;c.</hi> pag. 50. OR THE SACRAMENTAL COMMUNION.</head>
               <p>WE are now come to the actual receiving of the Body and Bloud of <hi>Christ,</hi> which is a Feast, whereunto the Faithful are invited, as to an Earnest of that Heavenly Banquet, which the Blessed enjoy above. <hi>David,</hi> when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the <hi>Ark of the Covenant</hi> into his house, with joy; <hi>Cum gaudio, 2 Reg.</hi> 16. 12. And <hi>Zacheus,</hi> who received the Son of <hi>God</hi> with the like joy, <hi>Excepit illum gaudens, Luc.</hi> 19. 6. are the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of those Holy Soules, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scious of their own unworthiness, do humbly receive and feed upon this <hi>Bread of Angels: For my Flesh is meat indeed,</hi> saith our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 6. 56.</p>
               <p>Now, the chief effect of this Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stial Food, is to unite the Faithful with <hi>Christ,</hi> and the Faithful among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; for by the <hi>Eucharist</hi> our Soules
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:63525:101"/> are espoused to <hi>Christ,</hi> and we become flesh of his Flesh; <hi>Qui manducat meam carnem—in me manet, &amp; ego in eo, Joan.</hi> 6. 57. And by this wonderful design of <hi>Christ,</hi> breathing nothing but unity, he also mutually unites the Faithfull one to another, how different soever they may be in their conditions or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests; for since they all eat the same Divine food, which hath a miraculous power to change and convert them in it self, it communicates to them such an union as composeth all their differences.</p>
               <p>This double union is excellently fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured by the Bread and Wine; the one made up of many grains of Corn, the other of many grapes of the Wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:63525:101"/>
               <head>OF THE SPIRITUAL <hi>COMMƲNION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THey, that for some impediment of Body or Soul, cannot receive well the Sacramental Communion, should at least make a Spiritual one by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving in desire and affection, as the <hi>Council of Trent</hi> doth earnestly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, <hi>Sess. 22. cap.</hi> 6. otherwise, so far as it lies in them, they render the Oblation of the Sacrifice imperfect, by not applying to themselves the merits and fruits of the <hi>Cross;</hi> which <hi>Spiritual Communion</hi> many be made in these or the like terms, while the Priest is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Bountifull JESƲS, who doest not only accept the pious actions of men, but even their Holy desires; Behold I a poor sinner present my self to receive in a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual way, what I dare not in a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental. Behold I open the mouth of
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:63525:102"/> my Soul, and I stretch forth to Thee the arms of my desires. Come, O dear JESƲS, come then that my Soul may at least pick up some few crumbs of thy Divine Grace. Lord JESƲS, who doest invite us to this Bread of Angels, look graciously upon me, as thou didst upon the poor</hi> Publican <hi>stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off, and knocking his breast, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from me, what may be displeasing to Thy Sacramental presence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="part">
            <pb n="191" facs="tcp:63525:102"/>
            <head>✚ THE FIFTH PART, Called the POST-COMMUNION, THAT IS THE THANKSGIVING. Answering to what was done by the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Old Law, after their eating of the PASCHAL LAMB.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the Post-Communion in general.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is not sufficient for the nourishment of Mans Body, that he eat ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Bread, and let it down into his stomack, unless it be also digested by his natural heat, and turned into his substance: So it is not enough to
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:63525:103"/> eat and receive into his stomack this Bread of Angels, come down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, unless it be in some measure spiritually digested by the heat of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: that so it may transform the <hi>Christian,</hi> and make him become as it were another <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> once complained, that his heart was dry'd up like grass cut in a field: <hi>Because,</hi> saith he, <hi>I have forgot to eat my bread;</hi> He doth not say, because I have forgot to <hi>take it,</hi> but to eat my bread: <hi>Oblitus sum comedere panem meum, Psal.</hi> 101. 5. For People often take this Sacred Bread, but do not eat it: That is, they make it not pass into the nutriment of their Soules, When <hi>Christ</hi> said to the <hi>Apostles; Take and eat,</hi> he seems to intimate thereby, that many would receive it, who would not eat it in the sense above-said.</p>
               <p>To eat it profitably, and to change it into the sustenance of our Soules; we must have greater reverence towards it, after we have received it, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we actually receive it. But by a strange abuse, the contrary is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently done; for too many after they have received it, think no more of it.
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:63525:103"/> In which they do like him that should make great preparations to entertain a Prince at his House, and when he is once entred, should leave him there alone, without attending upon, or shewing him the least respect.</p>
               <p>We should carefully consider what St. <hi>Bonaventure</hi> and other <hi>Fathers</hi> remark, that to receive unworthily, is not only to receive the Body of <hi>Christ</hi> in mortal sin; but likewise not to receive it with that reverence, and attention that is due to it. Nor is this reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to be given, for the moment only of our receiving, or for the time that preceds the <hi>Communion;</hi> but we ought in all our following actions, to demean our selves, as having in some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees been made partakers of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable Mystery.</p>
               <p>And of this comportment and recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the <hi>Manna,</hi> (which fell not upon the <hi>Sabbaoth</hi> day) was a figure; God commanding the <hi>Jews</hi> to remain at home: <hi>Maneat unusquisque apud semet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipsum, Exod.</hi> 16. 29. By which figure we are instructed, that at least, for the day of our receiving this Heavenly Gift, we ought to remain at home: That is,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:63525:104"/> to lay aside all worldly cares, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our selves interiourly, to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of this Divine Mystery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>THE ANTHEM, Termed <hi>COMMƲNION,</hi> pag. 52.</head>
               <p>THis Anthem is usually a Versicle of a Psalm, sung in a cheerful tune, while the Priest and the People are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Blessed <hi>Communion,</hi> whence it takes its denomination of <hi>Communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, the reason why this Anthem is sung in a cheerful tune, is, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press the joy and transports of a Soul sitting at this Heavenly Banquet, and relishing the sweetness of this Divine Food, figured by the <hi>Manna,</hi> which Scripture tells us, to have had the taste of <hi>Honey; Exod.</hi> 16. 31. Yet none but perfect Soules do relish this Sweetness, which is therefore stiled by St. <hi>John,</hi> the <hi>hidden Manna,</hi> Apocal, 2. 17.</p>
               <p>The cheerful tune of this Anthem is incomparably well figur'd, in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Book of <hi>Kings,</hi> where it is said of <hi>David;</hi> that when he brought the
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:63525:104"/>
                  <hi>Ark of the Covenant</hi> into his City, he dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced before it, with all his force: <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabat totis viribus ante Dominum, 2 Reg.</hi> 6. 14. This Mysterious dance, saith a Great Doctor of the <hi>Church,</hi> is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable picture of Christian Life. For as in dancing all the steps are order'd according to the tune and cadence of the <hi>Musick;</hi> so in a Christian Life, all the steps are to be order'd according to the sound and harmony of the word of God, as being the Rule of our lives; the Scripture saying, that God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects the steps of Man, <hi>Apud Dominum gressus hominum dirigentur, Psal.</hi> 36. 23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Post-communio, <hi>pag.</hi> 54.</head>
               <p>THis is the publick Prayer said after the <hi>Communion,</hi> in praise and thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving to God for all the Blessings we have received. This is done in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Christ</hi> himself, of whom the <hi>Evangelists</hi> write, that after the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> at his last Supper, he sang a a Canticle of Thanksgiving: <hi>Et hymno dicto, Matth.</hi> 26. 30.</p>
               <p>This was the Jewish custom, as we learn it out of their Ritual and Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:63525:105"/> Books: For after they had eaten the <hi>Paschal Lamb,</hi> they passed a good part of the night in singing Psalms to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. And as for the Canticle or Psalms which they sung after this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterious Supper, <hi>Baronius ad An. 34. Brugensis,</hi> and others hold, that it was the six Psalms, that bear the title of <hi>Alleluia.</hi> And to these six, a seventh is added by <hi>Cornelius a Lapide.</hi> The whole seven are these:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Laudate pueri Dominum, 112.</item>
                  <item>In exitu Israel, 113.</item>
                  <item>Dilexi, quoniam, 114.</item>
                  <item>Credidi, propter, 115.</item>
                  <item>Laudate Drim omnes gentes, 116.</item>
                  <item>Confitemini Domino, 117.</item>
                  <item>Beati immaculati, 118.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Now, the Collect and Prayer in the <hi>Mass</hi> called the <hi>Post-Communion,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers to that Thanksgiving of the <hi>Jews.</hi> And though our <hi>Pest-Communion</hi> seems very short in respect of the Jewish Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, yet we must consider, that our Even-Song or <hi>Vespers,</hi> is but an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the <hi>Post-Communion.</hi> And therefore on <hi>Easter</hi> eve, instead of the
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:63525:105"/>
                  <hi>Post-Communion,</hi> immediately after the <hi>Communion</hi> in the <hi>Mass, Ite Missa est,</hi> is said after Even-Song.</p>
               <p>By what hath been said, we may learn how to hear Even-Song with the same intention the <hi>Church</hi> had in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining it. That is, to mind and praise God, for the grace and Blessings we have received in the Sacramental or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>Communion.</hi> And if we reflect on the substance of the Psalms said on Sunday at Even-Song, we shall find, that they all relate to the <hi>Communion</hi> of the same day.</p>
               <p>For instance; the first Psalm <hi>Dixit Dominus, &amp;c.</hi> is all in praise of the Priesthood of <hi>Christ.</hi> In the Psalm <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitebor, &amp;c.</hi> we praise God for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Food he hath bestow'd upon us, <hi>Escam dedit timentibus se.</hi> By the Psalm <hi>Beatus vir qui timet Dominum,</hi> we are encouraged to the observation of Gods Commandments, in order to a frequent <hi>Communion,</hi> which is the happiness at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable in this life. The Psalm <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date pueri Dominum,</hi> is an invitation to praise God, for his wonderful care in providing this Sacrament, for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of our Soules. By the Psalm <hi>In
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:63525:106"/> exitu Israel,</hi> we praise Gods Bounty, for our delivery from sin, by this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of our Religion. The Canticle <hi>Magnificat</hi> spoken by the <hi>Blessed Virgin,</hi> is a precedent for us to imitate, when we have received her Blessed Son in the Sacred <hi>Communion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Ite Missa est, <hi>p.</hi> 54.</head>
               <p>THe Prayer of Thanksgiving being ended, the Priest, in saying <hi>Ite, Missa est,</hi> bids the People depart, and enjoy the Blessed fruits of the <hi>Communion</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When he sayes <hi>Benedicamus Domino,</hi> as he doth in <hi>Advent, Lent,</hi> and at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others times; he thereby invites the People to a further praising of God, according to their devotion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Benedicat vos, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 56.</head>
               <p>AT the end of <hi>Mass</hi> the Priest gives a Benediction to the People before they depart, as a Seal to close up the Blessings received in the <hi>Communion.</hi> This Form of blessing the People, God himself prescribed the Priests, saying: <hi>Sic bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicetis filios Israel—Benedicat, &amp;c.</hi> Num. 6. 23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:63525:106"/>
               <head>In principio erat Verbum, &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 56.</head>
               <p>AFter the Blessing, immediately fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the Gospel of St. <hi>John,</hi> which, containing the great Mysteries of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Persons, and of the Sacred Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>Christ,</hi> is hear read, to raise in us a hope and confidence of enjoying in the next Life a clear vision of the same Mysteries, by vertue of the Blessed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, received here on Earth.</p>
               <p>This our purchase of Heaven after this life, was notably figured to us by Mount <hi>Horeb,</hi> where the poor persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Elias</hi> arrived at last by the refresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he received from a small cake, and a pot of water brought by an Angel, while he lay sleeping under a Juniper tree, 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19. 6. This travel of <hi>Elias</hi> even to Mount <hi>Horeb,</hi> may signify the progress we are to make by holy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires and good works, even to the top of Christian Perfection. But in this pilgrimage our true bread and sustenance is the <hi>Body of our Saviour,</hi> given us by
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:63525:107"/> his Angels, that is, by his <hi>Priests.</hi> And the dew of Gods Grace, is that which is signify'd by the pot of water given to <hi>Elias</hi> with his cake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>THE CONCLƲSION.</head>
               <p>FRom what hath been said, let us conclude, that the <hi>Mass</hi> is a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury of all Godliness, and an <hi>Aggregate</hi> of all Christian Sacrifices together. And that the Faithful in the first, and the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Parts of the <hi>Holy Mass,</hi> prepare themselves to the Great and Visible Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, by less perfect and spiritual ones: As by the Sacrifices of Confession, and of a penitent heart, at the <hi>Introibo,</hi> the <hi>Confiteor,</hi> and the <hi>Kyrie eleison:</hi> By Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of Petition, Prayer, and Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, at the <hi>Collects, Secreta,</hi> and the <hi>Post-Communion:</hi> By Sacrifices of Praise, and Invocation, at the <hi>Introit,</hi> the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria in Excelsis,</hi> the <hi>Gradual, &amp;c.</hi> By Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of Humility and Obedience, in submitting our understanding to the will of God, read in the <hi>Epistle</hi> and <hi>Gospel:</hi> By a Noble Sacrifice and Profession of
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:63525:107"/> our Faith, at the <hi>Creed:</hi> and finally by generous Sacrifices of our Fortune and Estate, at the <hi>Offertory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At last, from such interiour Sacrifices (practised by <hi>Christ</hi> with his <hi>Apostles</hi> in the Divine Prayer, and admirable dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course he made to them, before his Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, <hi>John</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17.) doth the Priest pass to the Action of the Great Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, which (besides what hath been said Chapter 3d.) differs from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Cross in this particular; That on the Cross <hi>Christ</hi> offer'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self for all Men, when the generality of Men neither offer'd him, nor joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly offer'd themselves with him. But on the Altar, <hi>Christ</hi> not only offers himself, but is also offered by Men: For the Church offers him to God, and offers her self with him. In fine, <hi>Christ</hi> offers himself for the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowes himself upon her, and presents her to God.</p>
               <p>Is it not then most unworthily done, to assist at so Holy a Mystery, without due attention, and rather out of custom, than piety. Therefore do I beseech all good Christians to take heed of their promise, and not to be found lyars
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:63525:108"/> in the presence of God, when the Priest bidding them to lift up their hearts saying, <hi>Sursum corda;</hi> they answer, we do, <hi>Habemus ad Dominum.</hi> For God ought not to be pray'd to, with the only sound of the voice, but with a pure and elevated mind. And thus, I hope (Christian Offerer by your good prayers, which you cannot well deny me) to become par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of those Great Blessings, which the Church obtains from God the Father, by this most efficacious Oblation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="epigraph">
               <head>
                  <bibl>Offic: Eccles. in Festo Corp. Christi.</bibl>
               </head>
               <l>Vetustatem novitas,</l>
               <l>Ʋmbram fugam veritas</l>
               <l>Noctem, lux eliminat.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:63525:108"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg 72, Line 9. for <hi>appointed,</hi> read <hi>pointed.</hi> p. 75, l. 26. for 2. 39. r. 23. p. 81, l. 28. for <hi>debt,</hi> r. <hi>debt be.</hi> p. 82, l. 13. for <hi>thought,</hi> r. <hi>taught.</hi> p. 83, l. 12. for <hi>Thynnaim,</hi> r. <hi>Thymiama.</hi> p. 91, l. 5. for <hi>alterum,</hi> r. <hi>alterum habitum.</hi> p. 100, l. 8. for <hi>more,</hi> r. <hi>most.</hi> p. 145, l. 26. for <hi>pray,</hi> read <hi>praise.</hi> p. 149, l. 25. for <hi>Isiod.</hi> r. <hi>Isid.</hi> p. 110. l. 23. for <hi>substituted,</hi> r. <hi>substitute.</hi> p. 159, l. 9. for 9. 10. r. 9. 11. pag. 167, l. 21. for <hi>Gift,</hi> read <hi>the Gift.</hi> p. 188, l. ult. for <hi>Wine,</hi> r. <hi>Vine.</hi> p. 200, l. 13. for <hi>imperfect,</hi> r. <hi>less perfect.</hi> p. 201, l. 16. for <hi>himself,</hi> r. <hi>him.</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:63525:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:63525:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:63525:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:63525:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:63525:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:63525:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:63525:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:63525:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:63525:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:63525:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:63525:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:63525:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:63525:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:63525:117"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:63525:118"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:63525:118"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:63525:119"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:63525:120"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:63525:120"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:63525:121"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:63525:121"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>